<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Christian commemoration, and imitation of saints departed explicated, and pressed from Heb.13.7. Occasioned by the decease of the Reverend Mr. Henry Hurst, lately minister of the gospel in London. By Daniel Burgess.</title>
            <author>Burgess, Daniel, 1645-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 139 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 68 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30273</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B5698</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224015</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99834688</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99834688</idno>
            <idno type="VID">39192</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30273)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 39192)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1808:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Christian commemoration, and imitation of saints departed explicated, and pressed from Heb.13.7. Occasioned by the decease of the Reverend Mr. Henry Hurst, lately minister of the gospel in London. By Daniel Burgess.</title>
                  <author>Burgess, Daniel, 1645-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Parkhurst at the Bible and Three Crowns in Cheapside near Mercers chapel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Congregational Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Hebrews --  Commentaries --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Christian life --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:39192:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39192:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To <hi>ISRAEL MAYO,</hi> Eſquire, and <hi>ELIZABETH</hi> his Wife, of the County of <hi>Hartford.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Excellent Friends,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IN the days of old time, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Men did ſet up <hi>Stone Monu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> in the places where they received <hi>extraordinary Mercies.</hi> That cuſtom obtains not in Chriſtian practice. Otherwiſe I had haſtned to Build one in your delicious <hi>Bayford place.</hi> In your <hi>Bethel</hi> there, and my Children's <hi>Bethlehem.</hi> The <hi>Houſe of their Bread</hi> for a long time. Bread, bleſſed to be <hi>the Staff of a very ſinking and almoſt hopeleſs life</hi> in one of them.</p>
            <p>A <hi>Paper Memorial</hi> I have thought bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than <hi>none.</hi> And do hereon inſcribe my acknowledgments unto the <hi>Father</hi> of Mercies, and to your ſelves his <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments. Bleſſed be God, and bleſſed be you from God! Amen and Amen!</hi> Unto the <hi>divine Grace,</hi> be <hi>Sacrifices of praiſe</hi> for ever. Unto <hi>your ſelves,</hi> be the Joy of <hi>a good Foundation againſt the time to come!</hi> The Holy Ghoſt ſo names
<pb facs="tcp:39192:2"/>your works of <hi>Beneficence;</hi> or as ſome <hi>Criticks</hi> conſtrue it, <hi>a Bill of Contract;</hi> by vertue whereof you have your fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Judge</hi> made your <hi>Debtor,</hi> and the <hi>Day of Judgment</hi> enſured to be the <hi>Day of Payment.</hi> The <hi>Hebrews</hi> do call <hi>Alms</hi> by the name of <hi>Salt,</hi> for its <hi>preſerving</hi> and <hi>ſweetning</hi> power. And the great <hi>Alphonſus</hi> uſed to ſay, that <hi>he kept the very things he beſtow'd.</hi> Implying, that, by honouring God with his ſubſtance, he did not <hi>Alienate</hi> it, but <hi>Confirm</hi> his Propriety, in it. By your <hi>liberal things towards me deviſed,</hi> I am made a witneſs of your ſacred Unanimity. May your reward be <hi>great, preſſed down, ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken together, and running over.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of <hi>this Diſcourſe</hi> whereto I have prefixt your Names, I have many ways ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed my humble thoughts. That <hi>great Man,</hi> whoſe weighty ones follow in <hi>his Letter unto me</hi> here annexed, is the only one from whom I have received much light in the Argument. I never heard one <hi>Sermon</hi> hereof; nor read ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Lines,</hi> except in a Chapter of his <hi>Life of Faith.</hi> A Chapter <hi>worthy to be written in Cedar, and to be read as long as Letters laſt.</hi> And if I could have given to my Friends, half the number of thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:39192:2"/>
               <hi>Chapters,</hi> that I can of theſe <hi>Sermons,</hi> I ſhould not have now ſent them abroad, after ſo many Months confinement in my <hi>Cloſet.</hi> I think I ſhould have let them paſs through no more <hi>Honour and Diſhonour, good Report and evil Report,</hi> than had fallen upon them in the Preaching. Of your candid acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I have no doubt in my Breaſt; and therefore make no needleſs intreaties for its welcome in your Houſe.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <salute>My great Benefactors,</salute>
               <p>My <hi>daily Prayers</hi> aſcend for your <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,</hi> and your numerous and lovely <hi>Branches. Prayers,</hi> that all the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Divine Love</hi> may be the reward of your <hi>Families Love</hi> unto mine. That you may, all, be reaping <hi>to Eternity,</hi> the Kindneſſes you have vouchſafed to the <hi>Apples of my Eye.</hi> And that all the days of your Lives, your <hi>Treaſures, Hearts, Companions</hi> and <hi>Converſations,</hi> may verily be <hi>where this Diſcourſe directs them!</hi> That, as <hi>your ſelves,</hi> your <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> may become, <hi>all of them,</hi> eminent inſtances of the poſſibility of <hi>Camels running through the Needles Eye;</hi> of <hi>Rich Folks</hi> entering the <hi>Kingdom of Heaven.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:39192:3"/>That if your long <hi>Proſperity</hi> abide, it may not <hi>ſlay,</hi> or ſo much as <hi>wound</hi> you. And if <hi>Adverſity</hi> do <hi>overtake,</hi> it may ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>overcome</hi> you. Finally, That the leaſt of Chriſt's Miniſters that have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained Mercy to be Faithful, may be made no unprofitable Servant to your holy Joy of Faith. Even</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your true Honourer, and very thankful Servant in Chriſt Jeſus, <hi>Daniel Burgeſs.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>From my Study in <hi>Bridges</hi> ſtreet in <hi>Covent-Garden,</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug. 28. 1690.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter_to_the_author">
            <pb facs="tcp:39192:3"/>
            <head>Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s Letter to the Author concerning this Diſcourſe.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough you ſent me your <hi>M. S.</hi> as if it were to know my thoughts of it, I am ready to conjecture that you did it in Charity, to be a help to a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anguiſhing dying Man: And I muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay that I have long found a great deal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f benefit, by the Exerciſe of the Duty which you preſs: But you have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one it ſo very well for matter and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anner, as I hope will much add to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he pleaſing aſcent of my Affections. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have long ſuppoſed that God (tho' <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>very where equally in his Eſſence, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et not equally working every where, and on all things) doth firſt operate uſually on the higheſt Creatures, that
<pb facs="tcp:39192:4"/>are likeſt him in excellency, and by them on the lower, and ſo to the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt: And that, accordingly, to the aſcent of the loweſt there muſt be ſome advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage given by thoſe next them. Though we are unacquainted with the cauſality of moſt of the ſuperior mediate Cauſes, except thoſe whoſe knowledge is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to our Duty. As we know that there is one Mediator between God and Man, whoſe Office and Honour no Creature muſt invade; ſo we know that he uſeth variety of inferior means, Angels and Men, Apoſtles, Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors, Rulers, Ordinances, and many below theſe.</p>
            <p>And they that will have nothing but God immediately, will have none of God: To ſet God againſt ſecond Cauſes natural or gracious, is to ſet him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his own Work, his Wiſdom and his Will, and that is to ſet him againſt his own Glory and Himſelf; I never believed that he that praiſeth an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Fabrick, doth thereby diſhonour the Builder: And he that ſaid, <hi>As
<pb facs="tcp:39192:4"/>my Father ſent me, ſo ſend I you,</hi> and <hi>he that heareth you heareth me,</hi> did not thereby ſet up ſo many Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſts, nor diſhonour himſelf.</p>
            <p>Far be it from us to aſcribe any of Gods Prerogative to any Creature. <hi>Juſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin Martyr</hi> ſaith, <hi>He would not have believed Chriſt himſelf, if he had Preached any but the true and only perfect God.</hi> But infiniteneſs even of Perfection overwhelmeth us if our Thoughts approach him not by a Mediator, of whom as in our nature we have more familiar thoughts: And certainly Chriſt would not have us pretend to glorifie him as ſeparated from his Church: The Glory of the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> was ſhewed <hi>John</hi> in its particulars, for the exerciſe of his Faith, and the raiſing of his Deſire, Hope and Joy. Chriſt is not there ſolitary, nor would ſo be thought of. To ſit down with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> is part of the promiſed Felicity.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:39192:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:39192:5"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:39192:6"/>
            <p>Some men think they diſhonour Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and Saints, if they deſcribe not their Perfection, too like to that of God himſelf; and ſet not Man a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove Man, yea above Angels; yea ſome Deifie Souls on Earth it ſelf, feigning their Spirits as diſtinct from Soul and Body, to be Specifically Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentiated, by the Eſſence of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or as others of the ſecond and third Perſons in the Trinity, which they ſay are the Prime Emanant Life and Matter, and this not only as the <hi>Efficient,</hi> but <hi>Conſtitutive</hi> Cauſe. A Heaven of mens own feigning, will be no Heaven.</p>
            <p>Though you know who (Mr. <hi>F.</hi>) correcteth me for thinking that there is Repentance in Heaven, I am ſo far from thinking otherwiſe, that I dare not pray for to be freed from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting there. A Heaven conſiſtent with an Everlaſting penitent ſenſe, that I ſinned, and thereby needed a Saviour, Mercy and Forgiveneſs, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citing me to the joyful praiſes of him
<pb facs="tcp:39192:6"/>that Redeemed us, and waſhed us from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur ſins in his Blood, ſuch a Heaven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill ſatisfie my hopes. I believe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll Sin and Curſe ſhall be done away; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut I think ſuch a Repentance is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>her Sin nor Curſe.</p>
            <p>As I live in almoſt continual thoughts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Heaven, ſo the remembrance of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ultitudes of my old holy Acquaintance, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeldom left out of theſe thoughts. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd there are few ſleeping nights in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hich I dream not of ſome or other of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem.</p>
            <p>And, if it be a weakneſs, I will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nfeſs it to you, that I have much ado <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> think but ſome ſhame with confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>on will accompany me, when I firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eet any there that I have been unkind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, or wronged; and that will know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y faults better than here they did; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd that I ſhall ask them forgiveneſs: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which I know being forgiven by Chriſt they will ſoon grant.) I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oſe you have read or heard of my Dear and Holy Friend Dr. <hi>Drake</hi>'s Letter to Mr. <hi>Love</hi> before his Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<pb facs="tcp:39192:7"/>I go not ſo far; but with my<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> thanks for your excellent Books, I tel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you, that waking and ſleeping, living, and I hope dying, I cannot ſpare in my Meditations of Heaven, the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant familiar thoughts of my Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance gone before, with all the bleſſed Body of Chriſt.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>With ſuch thoughts is paſſing, your un<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>worthy Brother<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Rich. Baxter.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Aug.</hi> 21. 1690.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:39192:7"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Men and Brethren,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Supreme Lord hath wonderfully diſtinguiſh'd men, in the condition of <hi>Living.</hi> But all are equal in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e neceſſity of <hi>Dying.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>David,</hi> a <hi>King,</hi> proclaimed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>f a <hi>Worm.</hi> And alas! we ſee and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el it, <hi>The Prophets do not live for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er.</hi> Tho', bleſſed be God, our <hi>great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rophet</hi> dies no more; but is with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Church to the end of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orld. The beſt of the <hi>Church</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uſt be taken out of the <hi>World.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>racious Perſons muſt Die to be <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ved;</hi> as Graceleſs ones muſt Die <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be <hi>Damned.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Churches <hi>Angels</hi> be not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ortal. Mr. HENRY HURST was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t; for <hi>God has taken him.</hi> You <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow this good Man is fallen. You
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:39192:8"/>know it; you have, and you do ſtil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> bewail it. <hi>So</hi> Samuel <hi>died, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Iſraelites were gathered together<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and lamented him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Many of you have heard a ver<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeaſonable and uſeful <hi>Sermo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> preach'd at his <hi>Funeral</hi> in this pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> And many more would have hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it, if the <hi>Place</hi> had been lar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> enough to receive them. All of yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> if I miſtake not, are melted into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> good diſpoſition for another Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon on the ſame Subject. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Eſteem</hi> for him, and <hi>Affection</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your ſelves, have inclin'd me to gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> you this.</p>
            <p>An Impulſe is faln on me, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> weak as I am) to undertake a thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> very great herein. Even, <hi>to raiſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Dead.</hi> To raiſe again this h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Man, and very many more. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> raiſe them in a very good ſen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and unto very good ſervice. Bett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> than it would be, if I could fet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> back their Souls from <hi>Abraha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> boſom, and their Bodies from t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:39192:8"/>Earth's bowels. Plainly Sirs, I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay in this Sermon, to raiſe of our <hi>bleſſed Brother,</hi> and of other <hi>glorified Brethren,</hi> tho' not the Lovely PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SONS, yet the holy FAITH, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly CONVERSATION, and the victorious END, Egreſs, or Going forth thereof into Glory. And all theſe, for your <hi>Inſtruction</hi> and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement</hi> unto Faith and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>neſs.</p>
            <p>I have found a <hi>Text,</hi> apt, (like the Archangel's Trumpet,) thus to raiſe the <hi>Dead,</hi> and change the <hi>Quick.</hi> To raiſe <hi>Dead</hi> Saints, and make more Lively the <hi>Living</hi> ones. A <hi>Text,</hi> which if I handle not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd you hear not amiſs, will do it. For it is the King of Heaven's Mandate given for the raiſing of them. And I will be bold to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay, <hi>If the mighty work be not done, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tis becauſe of our unbelief.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:39192:9"/>
               <epigraph>
                  <bibl>Heb. 13.7.</bibl>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>Remember them which have the rule over you, who have ſpoken unto you the Word of God: whoſe faith fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, conſidering the end of their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation: <hi>Or rather thus,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <p>Remember your Guides who have ſpoken unto you the Word of God whoſe Faith follow, conſidering the End (Eſcape, or Iſſue) of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation.</p>
                  </q>
               </epigraph>
               <p>I am of his mind, who hath ſaid; This <hi>Epiſtle</hi> to the <hi>Hebrews</hi> is as ſerviceable to the <hi>Church</hi> as the Sun is unto the <hi>World.</hi> But I wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> confine my preſent diſcourſe to this <hi>ſtricture</hi> of it, which is my Text<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The ſacred Writer is here preſſing unto <hi>Perſeverance</hi> in the <hi>Faith, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip,</hi>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:39192:9"/>and <hi>Obedience</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel.</hi> For promoting the ſame, he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes a duty, of which our <hi>Pulpits</hi> have been too ſilent, and your <hi>Pews</hi> too ignorant, if I rightly judge. The duty of recalling to mind <hi>Departed Miniſters;</hi> adding ſpiritual, mental <hi>Converſe</hi> with Dead ones, unto <hi>At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>endance</hi> upon Living ones. Making uſe of <hi>Comprehenſors,</hi> as well as of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>iators;</hi> of Teachers <hi>glorified,</hi> as well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of Teachers but <hi>imperfectly ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tified.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And of theſe, four things are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uired,</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Remembrance of their Perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Imitation of their Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Conſideration of their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Conſideration of the End and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ictorious Iſſue of that their Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are required, for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ellent and important End aforeſaid. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f theſe, the <hi>Connexion</hi> is too plain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be inſiſted on. For, the <hi>Imitation
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:39192:10"/>of the Faith</hi> of any, doth evidently enough require the <hi>honourable Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory</hi> of their Perſons. We have no <hi>Power</hi> to follow forgotten ſteps. Nor <hi>Will,</hi> to tread in any, but thoſe of reverenced Feet. And this lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, as evidently requires the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer. For Reaſon admits us not to <hi>Honour,</hi> or give our ſelves trouble to <hi>Remember</hi> ſuch, after whom we think not fit to walk. That were to be abſurdly prodigal of our <hi>Mind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Memories.</hi> Nor needs it be ſaid, either how neceſſary it is that we conſider firſt what mens <hi>Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation</hi> is, before we conſider what it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>bleſſed End</hi> is. Or how requiſite i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is unto our <hi>Imitation</hi> of the Faith o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Believers, that we have the motiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> conſiderations, of the <hi>gracious Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation</hi> in which it did begin, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the <hi>glorious Victory,</hi> in which i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> did end. For how uſeleſs to you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf were your moſt perfect Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>Heaven's Glory,</hi> if you coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> have it without a competent unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:39192:10"/>of the <hi>Work,</hi> whoſe <hi>Reward</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t is? And, who would take care to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ook much upon <hi>the Penny,</hi> before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e had took good cogniſance of <hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>abour in the Vineyard,</hi> whereof it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he wages? We muſt know the <hi>Race,</hi> before we <hi>can</hi> or <hi>ſhall</hi> liſt much to heed the <hi>Garland.</hi> And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ruly, till we ſee the difficulties of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he <hi>Race,</hi> to be run thorough by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>others; and the <hi>glories</hi> of the <hi>Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>and</hi> put upon their heads; we have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut little heart to <hi>Engage</hi> in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne, or <hi>Expect</hi> the other for our ſelves. Well it were, if by ſight of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oth we were duly animated.</p>
               <p>The ſubſtance of the Text I ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>abour to preſent in three orderly Poſitions; <hi>ſcil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. 1. <hi>Godly Miniſters, when Dead, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ught not to be Buried in Oblivion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. 2. <hi>Their holy Faith and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, ought to be conſidered and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>owed.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>P. 3. <hi>Conſideration of their Conqueſt and Eſcape out of all their Difficulties
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:39192:11"/>here below, is a very neceſſary motive to our imitation of their holy Faith and Life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I begin with the firſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <div n="1" type="doctrine">
                  <head>
                     <hi>P. 1.</hi> Godly Miniſters, when Dead, muſt not be Buried in Oblivion.</head>
                  <p>My Text expreſly commands the contrary. Remembrance of them, <hi>Natural</hi> and <hi>Moral,</hi> is here required. <hi>Naturally,</hi> we remember thoſe whom we often call to mind, think of, and ſpeak with our ſelves concerning them. For, thinking is nothing but ſpeaking with our ſelves. Thoughts be the words of our hearts. <hi>Morally,</hi> we remember ſuch as we do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruouſly ſpeak of with our ſelves. I mean agreeably to their worth; and ſuitably to the proper End of our commemorating them. This Moral remembrance, without the Natural, is <hi>impoſſible;</hi> and the Natural with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Moral, is at leaſt <hi>vain</hi> and <hi>idle. Remember your Guides,</hi> is in effect thus much; <q rend="margDblQuotes">Multiply ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and affectionate thoughts
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:39192:11"/>concerning them. Thoughts pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and apt to praiſe the Gifts and Graces of God in them, and to promote the ſame in your ſelves.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Our Engliſh Tranſlation renders <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> as a <hi>Partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> of the preſent tenſe:
<note place="margin">The Syriac, Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bic, Vulg. Lat. &amp; Rhemiſts; <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Grotius,</hi> and (of our own Writers) Doctor <hi>Owen</hi> and Biſhop <hi>Lloyd</hi> ſo take it.</note> But I rather conceive it a <hi>Noun Subſtantive</hi> in this place; becauſe the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks of ſuch as <hi>had been</hi> Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers; not ſuch <hi>as continued to be</hi> ſo. He ſeems to intend the <hi>Apoſtles, Evangeliſts,</hi> and all <hi>ordinary Paſtors</hi> who had led and ruled them by God's holy word; and were now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t reſt from their <hi>Labours,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oying their Reward. Theſe, he commandeth to be remembred; but not with any <hi>Heatheniſh</hi> or <hi>Popiſh</hi> Celebrations. Theſe, without the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eaſt particular deference unto St. <hi>Peter;</hi> or any ambitious pretending <hi>Succeſſors</hi> of his. Theſe, with a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>y apparent excluſion of all the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:39192:12"/>
                     <hi>Tribes,</hi> that take on them <hi>to Rule</hi> without <hi>ſpeaking the Word of the Lord.</hi> All, that Preach not, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Preach another Goſpel.</p>
                  <p>But, be it here obſerved; it is not <hi>only</hi> or <hi>principally,</hi> as <hi>Miniſters</hi> but as <hi>Members</hi> of Jeſus <hi>Chriſt,</hi> tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> we are charged to remember theſe <hi>departed ones</hi> aforeſaid. Their <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry</hi> of the Word, is indeed conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered as an <hi>Engagement</hi> unto the required Remembrance. But it i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> their <hi>Faith,</hi> their <hi>holy Converſation</hi> and the <hi>glorious End</hi> of both, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> are propoſed as <hi>ſpecially</hi> obligativ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thereunto. Inſomuch as my Tex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> may well admit a comprehenſion of all <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> that <hi>have fought th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> good fight, kept the Faith finiſhed their Courſe, and received their Crow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> I mean, of ſuch, as, tho' they wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> never called to the <hi>diſtinct Office</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the Miniſtry, yet in <hi>all manner of ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Converſation,</hi> have miniſtred unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> our Faith and Joy; as all ſeriou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> practical Chriſtians do. And, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:39192:12"/>whom after their Diſſolution, we may aſſert the things foreſaid, in <hi>Hope</hi> and <hi>Charity;</hi> (It being not for <hi>mortal Worms,</hi> to conclude peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torily, who do enter the <hi>heavenly Manſions.</hi>) I ſhall therefore confirm the <hi>Doctrine</hi> propoſed, as ſo far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended. And advance <hi>Conſiderations</hi> which do very convincingly prove thus much; <hi>ſcil. That godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters and Chriſtians, when they are Dead, ought ſo to be remembred as we have foreſaid.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <div n="1" type="consideration">
                     <p>
                        <label>C. 1.</label> 
                        <hi>Your reaſonable Nature binds you to remember your godly Miniſters and Friends deceaſed.</hi> It binds you to converſe moſt in your thoughts with the moſt noble Objects. But of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ll Creatures, excepting the bleſſed Angels, theſe are the moſt excellent. They are ſo in <hi>themſelves,</hi> and ſo in <hi>our Opinion,</hi> or rather your <hi>Faith.</hi> When they were in the Body, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ought them <hi>pieces of Heaven,</hi> of whom the <hi>World was not worthy.</hi> You <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>alled them <hi>the excellent of the Earth;</hi>
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:39192:13"/>and <hi>all your delight</hi> was in them How readily did you break from other <hi>Company,</hi> put off any diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable <hi>Buſineſs,</hi> and undertake <hi>Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neys,</hi> otherwiſe tedious, to ſolace your hearts with their Converſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> And are they now grown <hi>worſe</hi> for their very <hi>Perfection?</hi> Are they <hi>leſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Lovely</hi> for their being in <hi>Glory?</hi> B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> they therefore <hi>faln</hi> in your eſteem becauſe they are <hi>advanced</hi> unto Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? The <hi>nearer</hi> they be unto their Lord and yours, the <hi>farther</hi> muſt they be from all kind thoughts of yours? What hinders, that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not more delightfully viſit them now when all that is delightful fill them? That you cannot follow them to <hi>no worſe</hi> a Countrey, than you profeſs your ſelves ſeeking; and <hi>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> more remote,</hi> than that you hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> your Converſation in, if you an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> true Iſraelites.</p>
                     <p>It is full as eaſie to think of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> friend <hi>at the Indies,</hi> as <hi>at next doo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> And of your friends that be <hi>in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <pb n="13" facs="tcp:39192:13"/>houſe made without hands,</hi> as thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hat be <hi>in any houſe of your own</hi> here <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>elow. Wherefore, your own Minds, if you inhumanely reſiſt not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>heir Light and Law, will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cending unto theſe <hi>Stars in Glory.</hi> And that as naturally <hi>as the ſparks <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y upward.</hi> Or as Men, (impatient <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f herding with Creatures that live <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut an Animal Senſitive life,) do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſort for their pleaſure unto the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oſſeſſors of their own more noble Nature. And moſt Induſtriouſly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nto ſuch of them, as are of moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nſpicuous Goodneſs.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="consideration">
                     <p>
                        <label>C. 2.</label> 
                        <hi>Your gracious Love of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nds you to Remember your godly Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſters and Friends deceaſed.</hi> Love, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hich is <hi>all Religion,</hi> is of all things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e moſt <hi>Imperious.</hi> And, of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ings to be named, doth moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>and <hi>thoſe Legions of ours which are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>deſt to be Governed,</hi> our thoughts. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>endures not wilful <hi>Ignorance,</hi> or <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>getfulneſs</hi> of it's Object. It hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>en named very juſtly, the <hi>match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:39192:14"/>Art</hi> of Memory. <hi>Ubi Amor, ibi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Oculus.</hi> If the Love of God prevail in your <hi>Hearts,</hi> it will carry your <hi>Minds,</hi> and keep them where he is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> It will turn the ſtream of your cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and hold them toward Heaven. The Heaven, in which <hi>He</hi> is not without his <hi>Children</hi> with Him. Without the Souls <hi>of the ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> made perfect;</hi> who <hi>behold his face i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Righteouſneſs, and are ſatisfied with his Likeneſs.</hi> Every one exulting in that triumph about Him, <hi>My God i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> mine and I am His.</hi> And is it poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, think you, to Love <hi>this Father</hi> and not Love <hi>theſe Children</hi> of His to Converſe with <hi>Him,</hi> and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get <hi>them!</hi> with a neglectful <hi>Obliv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on of them,</hi> to hold an acceptabl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Communion with him!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The <hi>beloved Diſciple</hi> tells us un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitedly, concerning <hi>all</hi> his Family on <hi>Earth</hi> as well as <hi>Heaven; Eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> one that loveth him that begat, love<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> him alſo that is begotten of Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> 1 John 5.1. But <hi>what Children</hi> of h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="15" facs="tcp:39192:14"/>can we Love, if we Slight <hi>the very beſt</hi> He hath! And do <hi>then</hi> regard them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eaſt, <hi>when</hi> we conclude them to have moſt of his <hi>Image, Likeneſs,</hi> and <hi>Complacence.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="consideration">
                     <p>
                        <label>C. 3.</label> 
                        <hi>Your continued Relation unto godly Miniſters and Friends deceaſed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>inds you to the Remembrance of them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Sirs, you have been often charg'd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ot to look upon your ſelves too <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>bſtractedly;</hi> but to conſider your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>elves as Members of a <hi>Community.</hi> All the World, is, naturally, but <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ne Man and Woman's Children.</hi> The <hi>Church</hi> above and below, is but <hi>one Family.</hi> Beſides, as you cannot be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gnorant; the great Lord of this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>amily hath pleaſed, yet nearer to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>yn you, and thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſpeak of. To <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut you in <hi>particular endearing Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>tions</hi> unto them. Your <hi>Miniſters,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ow in glory, were, ſome of them, our <hi>Fathers,</hi> and begat you in Chriſt. Others were your <hi>Nurſes,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd fed and nouriſhed you in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>aith, after your New Birth. Your
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:39192:15"/>godly Friends, were (full often) the <hi>Miniſters of God for good unto you,</hi> in things Temporal and Spiritual. <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,</hi> you were all; <hi>Companions,</hi> and mutual <hi>Benefactors: ſerving one another in love.</hi> Now fain I would know, what you think! Doth ſuch <hi>Relation</hi> ſignifie <hi>little</hi> or <hi>nothing?</hi> Or, if it doth, was the Relation, and it's Obligations too, <hi>diſſolved</hi> at their Death? In the language of Practice, too many do ſo ſpeak; but you cannot ſo think. What! Doth Death <hi>ſeparate from God and Chriſt?</hi> Away with that frightful thought! <hi>Dead Saints be God's Friends.</hi> He calls <hi>Abraham</hi> his <hi>Friend,</hi> many hundred years after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe. <hi>Dead Saints be Chriſt's Friends</hi> alſo. He ſaith concerning dead <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus,</hi> Our <hi>Friend ſleepeth.</hi> Now, are they ſtill related to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and yet cut off from <hi>you?</hi> Dreadful imagination! But if, as it is moſt certain, the Relation is <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal;</hi> and ſtands in <hi>full force,</hi> what
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:39192:15"/>then? It follows evidently, that, as ſins <hi>againſt Relations</hi> be the moſt aggravated; forgetfulneſs of <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Friends</hi> is a ſin againſt everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Relations. And the guilty do in a very ill ſenſe, <hi>Forget their own people, and their Father's houſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="consideration">
                     <p>
                        <label>C. 4.</label> 
                        <hi>Your Gratitude binds you to remember godly Miniſters and Friends deceaſed.</hi> The <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> and all the <hi>Churches</hi> of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> owed thanks unto <hi>Aquila</hi> and <hi>Priſcilla.</hi> And owe you not <hi>any</hi> unto theſe, that have been your Helpers in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus?</hi> If you do, <hi>Contemptuous forgetfulneſs is a ſorry payment.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let it not <hi>offend,</hi> but <hi>excite</hi> to farther enquiry, ſuch as may doubt the truth of that which follows.</p>
                     <p>I cannot but think, that our god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Friends in Heaven do much more <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Remember us</hi> now, than when they dwelt in this <hi>cold</hi> and <hi>dark</hi> World. Their <hi>Love of God</hi> is <hi>now</hi> incomparably greater than <hi>before.</hi> And why not the <hi>Love of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:39192:16"/>all his Children,</hi> proportionably great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? Their <hi>Memories</hi> now are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected. And how then ſhould they forget the <hi>Brethren</hi> they but lately <hi>knew,</hi> and <hi>delighted</hi> in? Their Souls, by entring Heaven, receive an <hi>am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plitude</hi> that we can little expreſs. And they can there <hi>remember us,</hi> without <hi>diverting their minds from God.</hi> Yea, and be it heeded well; their <hi>Enjoyment</hi> of God above, as ours here below, doth not only <hi>Admit,</hi> but <hi>Require,</hi> affectionate thoughts of his Children. Our <hi>Prayers</hi> here are amiſs, if in them we forget our <hi>Brethren above,</hi> (as ſhall be afterwards ſhewn!) And their <hi>praiſes above</hi> would be amiſs if in them they forgat us, their <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren below.</hi> The reaſon is obvious; the <hi>King of Glory</hi> will be honoured and loved, by the honour and love of his <hi>Servants,</hi> for his ſake. And gives law unto thoſe in Heaven and Earth too, that they <hi>love each other as themſelves.</hi> Thoſe in Heaven, do
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:39192:16"/>fully obſerve it. The greater is our <hi>ſin</hi> and <hi>ſhame,</hi> that we are ſo little won by their admirable kindneſs: For,</p>
                     <p>Upon the ſuppoſition of this their kindneſs and mindfulneſs of us, this will be granted by all; To be <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful,</hi> is to be <hi>ungodly.</hi> And they are the moſt ungrateful Creatures on the <hi>Earth,</hi> who live forgetful of their Friends in <hi>Heaven.</hi> Being that ingratitude unto the greateſt Lovers of us, is the worſt that is poſſible to be in us.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="consideration">
                     <p>
                        <label>C. 5.</label> 
                        <hi>Your Character binds you to remember your Godly Miniſters and Friends deceaſed.</hi> You are <hi>Believers,</hi> are ye not? If ſo, the Spirit, that can neither be deceived nor deceive, deſcribes you as perſons <hi>Come up un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Spirits of juſt men made perfect.</hi> Heb. 12.22, 23. <hi>Believers,</hi> while they are in the State <hi>Militant,</hi> are took into the Society of their Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in the State <hi>Triumphant.</hi> They are come unto the <hi>City of the living
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:39192:17"/>God,</hi> the <hi>Heavenly Jeruſalem.</hi> They are made free <hi>Denizons</hi> and ſpiritual poſſeſſors of it; their <hi>Converſation</hi> is in it. They are come to the <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable Company of Angels,</hi> in that City. Not to this or that particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar <hi>Tutelar Angel,</hi> but to the whole Company. Not come to them, with their <hi>Prayers,</hi> as is the way of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Idolaters, who wildly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the <hi>Servants,</hi> to the reproach of the <hi>Lord.</hi> And againſt the <hi>Servants own holy Will. Worſhip me not,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Angel</hi> to St. <hi>John; I am thy fellow Servant and of thy Brethren.</hi> They are come to the <hi>Angels</hi> Society; who are gathered into that <hi>one</hi> Body, whereof <hi>Chriſt</hi> is the head. They are become <hi>Fellow Members</hi> with them, and have a <hi>Communion</hi> in ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice with them. <hi>Angels</hi> rejoyce in their good, and miniſter to it; and they rejoyce in <hi>Angels</hi> Bleſſedneſs and Glory. Nor is this at all Incre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, or Wonderful, if it be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered that they are come unto the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:39192:17"/>very <hi>Lord</hi> of the foreſaid City. <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God the judge of all.</hi> Come into a ſtate of <hi>Filial</hi> favour with Him. Have <hi>Acceſs</hi> unto him, and the Throne of his Grace, with ſweeteſt <hi>liberty</hi> and <hi>boldneſs.</hi> By means where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they come alſo to the <hi>Spirits of their Brethren made perfect.</hi> Being admitted thus to their <hi>Father,</hi> they are admitted unto all their ſo <hi>digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Brethren</hi> about his Throne. <hi>They are come to the Spirits of the juſt made perfect.</hi> The Dream of Spirits of juſt men <hi>departed,</hi> and not <hi>made perfect;</hi> but ſent to <hi>Purgatory</hi> to be refined; was never in the <hi>Apoſtle's</hi> Head. He knew none but <hi>perfect.</hi> And unto the Society of all ſuch, he declareth Believers acceſs. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, Believers, <hi>all,</hi> come. Not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s to Objects of their <hi>Worſhip</hi> and <hi>Invocation,</hi> or <hi>Mediators of Interceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> That were wretched <hi>Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my</hi> towards God, and <hi>Injury</hi> unto them. They come to them in way of <hi>Friendſhip</hi> and <hi>Communion</hi> with
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:39192:18"/>them. With them, who in their ſeparate ſtate from their <hi>own Bodies,</hi> do hold Communion with <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>all his Myſtical Body.</hi> With Chriſts Members <hi>on Earth,</hi> as truly as thoſe above <hi>in Heaven</hi> with them. Loving, and loved of all. A learned Man's words upon this Text, are memorable. <hi>We are ſaid here to come unto the Spirits of ju<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> men made perfect, in thoſe actings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> our minds wherein Evangelical Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion doth conſiſt. And this require<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> that there be like actings in them without which there can be no ſuc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Communion!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This being ſuppoſed; what muſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> we conclude of Souls eſtranged from their godly Friends <hi>departed?</hi> Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> very rarely afford unto <hi>perfected</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, one ſerious and ſteddy look o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> their thoughts. Who are far from taking it for their <hi>Duty,</hi> and mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it their <hi>practice,</hi> to have the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in their minds. And in the <hi>affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Memory,</hi> due unto <hi>ſuch a So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</hi>
                        <pb n="23" facs="tcp:39192:18"/>The leaſt we can ſay is this: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uch Chriſtians do foully <hi>blot their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ames, and fall ſhort of their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>acter, and live not up to their Eſtate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nd Dignity.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="consideration">
                     <p>
                        <label>C. 6.</label> 
                        <hi>Your Faith binds you to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member your godly Miniſters and friends deceaſed.</hi> I had almoſt ſaid, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>neceſſitates</hi> you. But of that, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>dge ye your ſelves, when you have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onſidered what follows. <hi>Faith,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ou muſt needs know, <hi>is the evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of Perſons, as well as of Things, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ot ſeen;</hi> not ſeen by Eyes of Clay. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>t were a <hi>ſorry buſineſs,</hi> if it were not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>. For it is only for the ſake of <hi>Perſons,</hi> that we <hi>do</hi> or <hi>ought</hi> to va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e any ſort of <hi>Things.</hi> But it is out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f queſtion; the Eye of Faith <hi>ſees Him that is Inviſible,</hi> Heb. 11.27. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Life of Faith, is fellowſhip <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd Communion with the <hi>Divine Perſons,</hi> 1 John 1.3. Say then, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>eſeech you; Can Faith ſee the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>her</hi> of Spirits, and hold Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n with the Father and Son; and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:39192:19"/>not with them that ſtand continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally before his <hi>Face,</hi> and neareſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> his <hi>Throne?</hi> The ſame Eyes of Fleſh that ſee the <hi>King,</hi> ſee his <hi>Attendant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> that ſurround him. Why ſhould not the ſame Eyes of Faith ſee th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Spiritual King,</hi> and his Attendants King's Children at <hi>greateſt diſtance</hi> uſe to have conſiderable Acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance and Friendſhip with the <hi>nea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> eſt in their Father's Court.</hi> Wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſhould hinder yours with your <hi>glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified Brethren,</hi> if indeed you hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> it with their <hi>Father in Heaven.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let me tell you, Sirs; the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> of Heaven, is a Lord of moſt <hi>nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> Hoſts. The <hi>Father of Spirits</hi> is not to be conceived of, as <hi>Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs.</hi> Nor the <hi>King of Glory,</hi> as ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on a <hi>Throne ſolitary.</hi> Or dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling in a <hi>thin Court.</hi> There is n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſuch God in Heaven, as is withou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> his <hi>thouſands, and ten thouſand time ten thouſand Spirits miniſtring unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Him.</hi> And, <hi>all, as ſpectable,</hi> as vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible unto Faith, as <hi>He himſelf.</hi> Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="25" facs="tcp:39192:19"/>ſo near unto him, that one would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hink it impoſſible to ſee <hi>Him,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ot ſee <hi>Them.</hi> All ſo like to Him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd ſo beloved by Him, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>empt of them is no ſmall contempt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f Himſelf.</p>
                     <p>The plain Inference then, is this. The <hi>Faith</hi> of living Saints faileth, before their <hi>Memory</hi> of the dead ones <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oth ſo. And the reaſon why we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o not more by Faith live <hi>with them,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> becauſe we do not by Faith live <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ore <hi>upon God.</hi> For a right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of Him, is inconſiſtent with the Forgetfulneſs of them, ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ear unto Him!</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="consideration">
                     <p>
                        <label>C. 7.</label> 
                        <hi>Your Intereſt binds you to Remember your godly Miniſters and Friends deceaſed.</hi> The intereſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>our <hi>Grace,</hi> and the intereſt of your <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Comfort</hi> doth bind you.</p>
                     <p>The Intereſt of your <hi>Grace.</hi> Need <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ou be told the Efficacy of <hi>Company?</hi> You have your glorified friends <hi>in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>our company,</hi> as oft as you have them in <hi>thoughtful memory.</hi> And of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:39192:20"/>ſuch their company, great is the double force: To wit, the <hi>Natural</hi> and the <hi>Inſtitutive.</hi> For, <hi>naturally</hi> we follow admired Examples. There's not one mind of a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, but receiveth impreſſions from them; juſt as <hi>Wax</hi> receiveth the figure of an <hi>applied Seal.</hi> Beſides <hi>God hath ordained a Communication of Qualities, from choſen Aſſociates. He that walks with the wiſe, ſhall be wiſe.</hi> God hath promiſed illapſes of their <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> into them that chuſe and hold their <hi>Communion.</hi> It cannot be therefore, but we muſt derive into us their heavenly Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, if in our thoughts we converſe much with our heavenly Friends. We muſt derive of their <hi>Love of God, Contempt of this World,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>The Intereſt of your <hi>Peace</hi> and <hi>Comfort,</hi> doth no leſs oblige you. That which ſerves your Grace, doth in ſo doing ſerve your Peace. But not alike, all. Nor ſcarcely any
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:39192:20"/>thing ſo <hi>immediately</hi> and <hi>ſenſibly,</hi> as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>leep and pious thoughts of glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Friends. Which will ſoon be but of queſtion, if you uſe but a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ittle conſideration. If you think a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ittle, what a refreſhment it muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e to be took now and then out of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n <hi>Hoſpital</hi> of ſick and crying Souls <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>r a <hi>Bedlam</hi> of mad and ranting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nes, into an houſe wherein all are <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>erry and wiſe.</hi> Alas! what is this <hi>World,</hi> but a <hi>mad Bedlam?</hi> What is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he <hi>Church on Earth,</hi> but a <hi>very Hoſpital,</hi> wherein no one is perfectly tured? What is <hi>Heaven,</hi> but the <hi>Colledge of all Souls without ſin or ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row?</hi> To retire in our minds from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he <hi>Bedlam</hi> and <hi>Hoſpital,</hi> into this <hi>Colledge.</hi> To leave a while the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects of our Grief, and go and enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain our thoughts with them who have none but of Joy. No words <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>an picture forth the ſweetneſs of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>his: Which is then <hi>always,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hen <hi>only</hi> known, when tryed. I mean, <hi>ſolemnly;</hi> not in ſlight and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nelaborate thoughts.</p>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:39192:21"/>
                     <p>They are therefore <hi>their own Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies,</hi> who bury in forgetfulneſs their deceaſed godly Friends. They rob themſelves of not the leaſt means of <hi>Grace</hi> and <hi>Peace:</hi> Wrong their <hi>own Souls,</hi> and that in their <hi>greateſt Concerns.</hi> Averting from ſo ſoveraign a courſe, both to <hi>Refine</hi> and <hi>Revive</hi> them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="consideration">
                     <p>
                        <label>C. 8.</label> 
                        <hi>Your God's Commands bind you to remember your godly Miniſters and Friends deceaſed.</hi> In my <hi>Text</hi> he commands, as you have heard, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.12. He commands you to be <hi>followers, imitaters,</hi> of them; and conſequently (I hope) to remember them. For <hi>Copies forgotten</hi> can by no means be imitated; or uſed for <hi>Examples,</hi> as is required, <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.10. <hi>All the Texts that ſet forth the ſtate of departed Saints,</hi> have ſo many commands going with them of your Remembrance contended for. You cannot think, that God leaves you at liberty, whether you will take and improve his <hi>Revelations,</hi>
                        <pb n="29" facs="tcp:39192:21"/>or no. Or, that any holy improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can be made of the ſame, while left in Oblivion. Waving all others, I will ſingly propoſe that one Text more, which I conceive <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>xtraordinary.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. <hi>Seeing we alſo are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ompaſſed about with ſo great a cloud <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>f Witneſſes; let us lay aſide every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eight, and the ſin which doth eaſily <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>eſet us, and let us run with patience <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>he Race that is ſet before us. Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ers,</hi> are here compared to <hi>men <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nning a Race.</hi> They are exhorted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o the <hi>means</hi> of running it, ſo that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hey may obtain the <hi>prize:</hi> To wit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y <hi>laying aſide weights,</hi> and <hi>ſins,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>xerciſing <hi>Patience</hi> with Diligence. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hey are encouraged ſo to run alſo. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ncouraged by <hi>Witneſſes</hi> given <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hem; a <hi>cloud,</hi> or <hi>great number</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hem; and this number placed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>und them, <hi>encompaſſing of them.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>heſe <hi>Witneſſes,</hi> are the Saints gone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>efore us to Heaven. Their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ony is either of that which we
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:39192:22"/>
                        <hi>do,</hi> or of that which we <hi>ought</hi> to do. As <hi>in the Races to which the Apoſtle alludeth;</hi> thoſe that did run uſed to have many Friends <hi>looking</hi> on them; and <hi>encouraging them;</hi> by teſtifying, either that thus they <hi>had</hi> done, or thus and thus they <hi>might</hi> and <hi>ought</hi> to do. In like manner, all the Saints above, do <hi>as it were</hi> ſtand looking on us. Not in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Speech, or <hi>intuitively;</hi> we have no ſuch Dream. But upon <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture-record,</hi> they do ſtill ſtand round about us. And are by their <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,</hi> for that purpoſe recorded; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging us in our <hi>Chriſtian race.</hi> Ready to teſtifie, how we acquit our ſelves. Though <hi>dead,</hi> yet they in a ſort <hi>ſee, ſpeak,</hi> and <hi>teſtifie.</hi> By their <hi>richly rewarded Duties,</hi> they teſtifie to the wiſdom of our <hi>moſt coſtly ones.</hi> Thoſe for which we are thought to be <hi>beſide our ſelves;</hi> and are moſt inhumanly dealt with by our Adverſaries. They are ready alſo to teſtifie what may be done in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:39192:22"/>every caſe, by us. Principally this; <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hat Faith will carry ſound Believers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>hrough all their Duties and Dangers.</hi> Upon many occaſions we fall into <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>onteſt with our ſelves, and diſpute, what is beſt. To <hi>go back,</hi> or to <hi>go <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n.</hi> And in a Wood, and loſt, we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re. Now theſe holy bleſſed Friends of ours encompaſs us. And their <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>erdict</hi> they do from the <hi>Holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ure Hiſtory</hi> give us. Teſtifying ſtill <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gainſt the <hi>frauds</hi> of all <hi>Temptations;</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>gainſt the <hi>folly</hi> of all our diſtract<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ng <hi>fears;</hi> and unto the <hi>Duty, Safe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>y,</hi> and <hi>ſure Victory</hi> of <hi>perſevering Faith.</hi> By conſequence it muſt be the Will of God, that, in all our Tryals, we ever and anon conſider the <hi>Eyes</hi> of theſe excellent Perſons thus upon us. And their <hi>Teſtimony,</hi> as hath been ſaid; that is ever upon the ſide of our Duty. That we do ſo conſider and lay this to Heart, as to turn it unto our <hi>motive encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> And a <hi>provocation</hi> to put forth the utmoſt of our Spiritual
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:39192:23"/>ſtrength. Whereby alone we can anſwer the gracious End of God, in vouchſafing unto us this encompaſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cloud, and encouraging one.</p>
                     <p>In ſhort; <hi>God</hi>'s <hi>Preceptive Will makes a perfect Neceſſity.</hi> And this his Will is revealed, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of Saints deceaſed! So that his <hi>Fear</hi> cannot be duly <hi>before your Eyes,</hi> when theſe <hi>Perſons</hi> are not duly kept <hi>in your minds.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="consideration">
                     <p>
                        <label>C. 9.</label> 
                        <hi>Your God</hi>'s <hi>promiſes do bind you to remember your Godly Miniſters and Friends deceaſed.</hi> Know ye not, that he hath promiſed an <hi>honourable</hi> and <hi>laſting</hi> Memory unto his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Servants! And that Memory <hi>to be among your ſelves;</hi> the only perſons Qualified to bear it. Now his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes ſpeak that <hi>Will of his,</hi> that is the <hi>Rule of yours.</hi> If you <hi>Conſent not</hi> to it, you Oppoſe your God. If you <hi>but Conſent</hi> to it, with an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>operative and Ineffectual Will; <hi>(Sola voluntas eſt cadaver, Scalig.)</hi> that is, as if you Conſented not. If
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:39192:23"/>you <hi>Conſent entirely,</hi> you remember thoſe we ſpeak of with ſweet me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory. And by that <hi>Practice</hi> ye fulfil the divine <hi>Promiſe.</hi> Add hereto; God hath honoured this gracious <hi>Practice,</hi> with conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>Promiſes</hi> unto ſuch as hold it. The very promiſe of <hi>dwelling in his holy Hill,</hi> is made unto ſuch as <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour them that fear Him.</hi> And 'tis a wonderful miſtake, if any think it made to ſuch as honour them, but for term of life. Such as honour them here, as the Excellent of the Earth; but ceaſe to honour them at all, when God honours them moſt; taking them to Heaven as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>udged to be too good for this World. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f this Promiſe then be a cord of Love, wherewith God draws us to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>he Honour and Love of the <hi>Saints in Light;</hi> as well as of the <hi>Houſehold of Faith;</hi> what muſt be inferred! They break it daringly, (do they not!) as many as Love and Honour Saints, but unto their Deaths. Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:39192:24"/>themſelves to have don their <hi>laſt Office</hi> indeed, when the have followed their <hi>Corps</hi> unto the grave's ſide. Giving the grave th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Victory over all their regards unto them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="consideration">
                     <p>
                        <label>C. 10.</label> Laſtly, <hi>Your own Prayer and Promiſes bind you to remembe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> your Godly Miniſters and Friends de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed.</hi> A word ſhall ſerve in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> plain Argument.</p>
                     <p>You pray that <hi>Gods will may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> done by you and by others on Earth, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> it's done in Heaven.</hi> As there it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> done, by all the Spirits about th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Celeſtial Throne. But how pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanely muſt you thus pray, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome very lively thoughts c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> thoſe Spirits, and of their Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence? Without which it is as if yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> prayed plainly, that his will may b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> done by you like you <hi>know not whom</hi> and as to manner, you <hi>mind n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> how.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Your <hi>Prayers</hi> all, are full of <hi>vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual promiſes.</hi> Praying that yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="35" facs="tcp:39192:24"/>
                        <hi>may,</hi> you do conſtructively promiſe that you will labour, to obey God as the Heavenly Hoſt do. Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently, that you will well conſider <hi>them,</hi> and their <hi>performances.</hi> Even with the accuracy and frequence of thoſe, who ſet themſelves to imitate greateſt <hi>Exemplars.</hi> And is it a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vial thing in your ſight, <hi>to lie unto God! And that in your very prayers!</hi> Or do you not ſo, if you exerciſe not your minds in the foreſaid conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of your glorifyed Friends.</p>
                     <p>Other conſiderations might be added; but I will hope, what is ſaid hath inforced your <hi>Belief;</hi> and raiſed in you full purpoſes, of <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience,</hi> unto this Truth.</p>
                     <p>Granting that it hath ſo done, ſome may ask, what will the <hi>Belief</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> of it make for Edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. Urging, that this remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Godly Miniſters and Friends deceaſed, is a ſubject they have <hi>rarely</hi> heard preached. And, notwithſtanding all the caution
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:39192:25"/>wherein it is expreſſed, it is one ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry liable to be abuſed unto Superſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.</p>
                     <p>I anſwer. If indeed it be a <hi>Trut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> the leſs it <hi>hath been</hi> inſiſted on, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> more it ought <hi>now to be</hi> inſiſted or And muſt not be kept from <hi>all</hi> Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, for fear it ſhould be abuſed b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſome. I have convincingly prove it to be a <hi>Truth.</hi> And one, who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> faith and regular Obedience contr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butes more than a little unto th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>love of God;</hi> unto the <hi>life of Faith</hi> unto all <hi>Grace and Conſolation.</hi> which I muſt believe, is to <hi>Edifie.</hi> Neve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> theleſs, I acknowledge it's uſe unt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Edification, to be more manifeſte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in the ſequel of this Diſcourſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Wherein are ſet forth thoſe hol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> things, whereunto the foreſaid R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> membrance is an <hi>Antecedent,</hi> bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> moſt <hi>Conducive</hi> and <hi>Neceſſary.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Wherefore I will but briefly ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt a few <hi>Inferences</hi> from this fir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and proceed unto a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="inference">
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:39192:25"/>
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 1.</label> 
                        <hi>The beſt of this World, muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ave it.</hi> In Death's War there's no Diſcharge. The <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Apoſtles</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>re dead. <hi>John</hi> the beloved Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>le, is not left behind.</p>
                     <p>It was the advice of a <hi>Heathen; Reckon your beſt friends as leaſt dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e things.</hi> And it is the Sentence <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>f holy <hi>Scripture, the Body is dead <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ecauſe of Sin,</hi> Rom. 8.10.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 2.</label> 
                        <hi>God honours them in their Deaths, that honour him in their lives.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd that here, where they have ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oured Him. For, as He commands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>e <hi>Church above,</hi> honorably to <hi>receive</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hem;
<note place="margin">So <hi>Chryſoſtom Clem. Vatablus. Menoch.</hi> and <hi>Lud. de Dieu (in loc.)</hi> conſtrue the Text.</note> He commands <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e <hi>Church below,</hi> hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>bly to <hi>remember</hi> 'em. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e will have their <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ames</hi> ſhine here, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ell as their <hi>Souls</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ere. <hi>Abel,</hi> ſo long ago murdered, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> to this day moſt honourably men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>oned, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Being dead, he is yet ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>en of,</hi> with renown immortal.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="inference">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:39192:26"/>
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 3.</label> 
                        <hi>Every Believer hath a</hi> Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob<hi>'s Ladder.</hi> I mean, he hath that, whereby he can in his Thoughts aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend the Heavens; and Spiritually view his glorified Miniſters an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Friends there. In his mind he ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſee <hi>where they are, what they are,</hi> and <hi>what they are doing,</hi> (as we ſhall here<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>after ſhew.)</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 4.</label> 
                        <hi>Sorrow for godly men deceaſed ought to be moderate.</hi> For we are t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> remember them <hi>honourably,</hi> and fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> imitation; not <hi>ſcandalouſly,</hi> to o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> diſtraction. True, we may, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ought to mourn. <hi>When</hi> Lazaru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>died; Jeſus wept.</hi> But we may n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſorrow <hi>unmixedly,</hi> and as witho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Hope. The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> mourned n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> ſo much for <hi>Jacob,</hi> as the <hi>Egyptia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> did. The grief of Saints, mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> know its bounds.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 5.</label> 
                        <hi>Although God be to be reme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred by us principally, he is not to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> remembred only.</hi> For he command<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> us to remember his and our ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Friends, that are in glory attendin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="39" facs="tcp:39192:26"/>him. Remember your <hi>Father;</hi> but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>orget not his Children, who carry <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>oſt of his Image and Likeneſs on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hem. Remember your <hi>Redeemer;</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ut forget not thoſe his Redeemed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n whom his Love and Power ſhine with greateſt Luſtre. Remember <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>our <hi>Sanctifier;</hi> but forget not his moſt Sanctified ones.</p>
                     <p>I conclude with a ſaying of one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>cquainted with God above thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ands: <hi>He never knew a heavenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>onverſation, that pretending to know God alone, hath no converſe with his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oly ones that attend Him; and doth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ot live as a Member of their Society <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>n the City of God; that doth not with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ome delight behold their Holineſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>nity and Order.</hi> But, as it is time, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> proceed to my next Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ion.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="doctrine">
                  <head>
                     <hi>D. 2.</hi> The holy Faith and Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation of godly Miniſters and Friends deceaſed, muſt be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered and followed.</head>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:39192:27"/>
                  <p>So the Text, in terms moſt plai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Follow their Faith;</hi> to wit conſidere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> by you. And that Comma, <hi>conſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the end of their Converſation</hi> imports evidently a <hi>command</hi> to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low it. For the ſake of theſe, wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> the <hi>remembrance of their Perſons</hi> fore required. Which, without th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> uſe of their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Converſatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> would be to little purpoſe. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> it conſidered therefore ſtrictly;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. What this <hi>Faith</hi> is.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. What this <hi>Converſation.</hi> And</p>
                  <p n="3">3. What the <hi>Reaſons</hi> for our co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering and following both.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Faith</hi> is conſidered as <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectively</hi> taken, or <hi>Subjectively.</hi> A the firſt, it is the truth of the Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel by them held. <hi>Viz.</hi> 1. Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>Goſpel-Hiſtory,</hi> of the <hi>Primiti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> Friendſhip</hi> between God and Man of the <hi>Enmity</hi> raiſed by the firſt ſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> between them; and of the <hi>Reconc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation</hi> made by the Son of God 2. The <hi>Goſpel Offer and Invitation</hi> of Sinners unto Grace and Salvation
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:39192:27"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y a <hi>New Covenant;</hi> one of admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>le <hi>Promiſes</hi> and moſt equitable and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>racious <hi>Demands.</hi> 3. The <hi>Goſpel-Rule</hi> and Directory for the <hi>Worſhip,</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd the whole <hi>Walk</hi> of all embracing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd entring that Covenant. This <hi>Hiſtory</hi> they <hi>Credited;</hi> this <hi>Offer</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hey <hi>Accepted;</hi> this <hi>Covenant</hi> they <hi>Entred;</hi> this <hi>Rule</hi> they <hi>Followed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ubjectively</hi> taken, their <hi>Faith</hi> is that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>race of God in them, whereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hey ſo received the Goſpel. Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>his grace of <hi>Faith,</hi> is either <hi>general;</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nd ſo 'tis their <hi>Aſſent</hi> and <hi>Conſent</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nto all God's Revelation as perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>y true: Or <hi>ſpecial;</hi> as it relates un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o <hi>Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> the ſum of all God's Revelation; and ſo it is their accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ance of Him in all his Offices, as <hi>Teacher, Saviour, Ruler.</hi> The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>arted Saints we ſpeak of, had a <hi>Faith,</hi> which was unto them inſtead of <hi>Poſſeſſion</hi> and <hi>Sight.</hi> One that made <hi>things ſaid by God,</hi> as credible as if they had ſeen them with their Eyes. And <hi>things promiſed by God,</hi>
                        <pb n="42" facs="tcp:39192:28"/>as comfortable as if they had had them in their hands. I would be underſtood of the <hi>Truth,</hi> only, not of the <hi>degree</hi> of Credibility and Comfort. They had alſo a Faith i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> their Hearts, which was unto them a <hi>Marriage Knot;</hi> whereby they joyned themſelves unto Chriſt Jeſus in everlaſting Covenant. Reſigning themſelves to him, to be <hi>Taught, Saved</hi> and <hi>Ruled.</hi> Committing themſelves to God's <hi>ſaving Mercy</hi> lodged in <hi>Chriſt's</hi> Hand: And ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting themſelves to God's <hi>govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Authority</hi> lodged in the ſame. This Faith of theirs, in both accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, is that which we are to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider and follow.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <p>
                        <hi>Converſation,</hi> is the way and courſe of humane life. Reſpective<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of all Duties; towards our <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, Redeemer,</hi> and <hi>Sanctifier;</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Church,</hi> the <hi>World,</hi> and <hi>our Selves.</hi> And this, as under all <hi>Circumſtances</hi> of our various <hi>Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> in our <hi>Pilgrimage.</hi> The way
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:39192:28"/>and courſe of the Saints we ſpeak of, was Holy and Exemplary. Through their Faith in Chriſt <hi>working by Love, purifying their Hearts, conquering the World,</hi> and <hi>chaſing the Devil,</hi> they ſincerely and perſeveringly glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified God. They held Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the <hi>Father, Son,</hi> and <hi>Spirit,</hi> in <hi>Faith, Hope</hi> and <hi>Love;</hi> in <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> and <hi>Obedience.</hi> They loved the <hi>Church</hi> as Chriſt's Body; ſerved it and ſympathized with it, as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of it. The <hi>Unregenerate World</hi> they pitied, and ſpent their days in pains and prayers for it's converſion. Their <hi>Hearts,</hi> that is, <hi>Themſelves,</hi> they kept with all diligence; pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring always the <hi>man</hi> above the <hi>Brute,</hi> the <hi>Soul</hi> above the <hi>Body.</hi> In a word, their life was an <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of Grace; a <hi>Warfare</hi> againſt Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions and Temptations; a <hi>put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of their Talents to Uſury,</hi> and merchandizing to and for Heaven. All their days, were <hi>Humiliation-days</hi> for their Sins, their <hi>Own</hi> and their
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:39192:29"/>
                        <hi>Relations;</hi> and <hi>Thanksgiving days</hi> for their <hi>Mercies</hi> and <hi>Hopes:</hi> They <hi>walked after the Spirit, and not after the Fleſh.</hi> And this their walk, is that their Converſation, that we are called to eye and to imitate.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="section">
                     <p>We ſhall briefly enquire the <hi>Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> for this practice. To wit of our <hi>conſidering</hi> the Faith and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of our glorified Brethren. And of our <hi>ſetting our ſelves to tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe both.</hi> Our own <hi>vanity,</hi> is apt to charge the Divine <hi>Wiſdom</hi> fool<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſhly, for commanding it. And to ask, <hi>Unto what purpoſe is this our coſt and pains?</hi> Being we have the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect rule</hi> of the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and of our <hi>Saviour's</hi> own tranſcendent <hi>Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s word is of great weight. WHY God commands a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing, I need not trouble my ſelf, He will look to that. Let me ever look well to WHAT he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. Whether we ſee them or no, there are <hi>infinite reaſons,</hi> for
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:39192:29"/>every thing God requires. But yet when thoſe reaſons are <hi>obvious,</hi> their uſe is <hi>rich</hi> and <hi>various.</hi> Of the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice foreſaid, I ſhall therefore point out a few ſuch as are moſt clear and apparent.</p>
                     <div n="1" type="reason">
                        <p>
                           <label>R. 1.</label> 
                           <hi>This practice unites the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per and lower Houſe of God.</hi> The Church above, and that below. It holds together the Members of the <hi>Family in Heaven and upon Earth.</hi> It engageth us, to keep eyeing of them. As Scholars of the lower Form, eye thoſe of the higher whom they muſt imitate. It even neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tateth the <hi>Houſhold of Faith,</hi> to hold great converſation with them that <hi>live by Sight.</hi> This is no light rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, with ſuch as conſider how God ſtands for his Children's <hi>Union</hi> and <hi>Aſſociation.</hi> Such as hath been fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoken of, and therefore ſhall have no more here ſaid of it.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="reason">
                        <p>
                           <label>R. 2.</label> 
                           <hi>This Practice doubles our help to the Life of Faith and Holineſs.</hi> The <hi>Inſtructions</hi> and <hi>Precepts</hi> of the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:39192:30"/>
                           <hi>Goſpel</hi> are a <hi>bleſſed</hi> Help. But not <hi>all,</hi> that we need. Who feels it not? After that we have heard our <hi>Maſter's beſt</hi> and <hi>brighteſt Doctrines,</hi> we need our <hi>Fellow Servants inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive and motive Examples.</hi> Which are indeed the moſt inſtructive <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> to the underſtanding of them; and moſt motive <hi>Encouragements</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the obeying of them; as <hi>Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi> certifieth. By what is here ſaid, no diſgrace is caſt upon the Goſpel. 'Tis meerly from our own dulneſs, that we need ſuperadded Examples. And the ſhame of that want, reſts ſingly upon our own Head. While in the mean time, unto God belongs the glory of the additional Mercy.</p>
                        <p>Admirable Mercy! For the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel ſhews us but the <hi>Duty.</hi> But the Example of deceaſed Saints ſhews alſo the <hi>poſſibility,</hi> of living by Faith and in Holineſs. Becauſe, what has been done, may certainly be done again. We are emboldned to
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:39192:30"/>believe we may ſo live, when we conſider others to have lived ſo. And let it not ſtartle you, if I ſay this: <hi>Jeſus Chriſt's own Example is (in this one reſpect) a much leſs en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, than one of his leaſt and pooreſt Servants.</hi> For it doth not <hi>nearly</hi> and <hi>immediately</hi> ſo teach the poſſibility of the foreſaid Life, as his Servant's example doth. A Soul under Temptation exclaims, that, be it ever ſo <hi>neceſſary,</hi> 'tis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together as impoſſible, to live by Faith in this World; and hold a rightly ordered Converſation in ſuch a Catholick <hi>Sodom.</hi> Go you and tell him, that the Son of God did <hi>live by Faith,</hi> and <hi>fulfil all righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> even in this World. He ſhall reply upon you, that it is a wild inference, that <hi>he</hi> may, becauſe the <hi>Son of God</hi> did ſo do. He ſhall tell you, Chriſt had none of <hi>his ſins</hi> in him; and he has little or none of <hi>Chriſt's ſtrength</hi> in his dejected Soul. Chriſt had all created and uncreated
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:39192:31"/>holineſs, and might well overcome <hi>World</hi> and <hi>Devil;</hi> but it were a wonder if they ſhould be overcome by him, a weak and ſinful Duſt. He ſhall ask you, what Logick of yours it is, that thus argues? An <hi>Angel</hi> ſlew an hundred thouſand E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies; therefore a <hi>Worm</hi> may ſlay as many. But, on the other hand; tell you this <hi>bruiſed Reed,</hi> that yon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in Heaven be <hi>multitudes,</hi> and <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of his own Acquaintance,</hi> that were Worms as <hi>weak</hi> as himſelf; as <hi>temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> as himſelf; and many a time as <hi>dejected</hi> as himſelf; who did, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs, <hi>keep the holy Faith,</hi> and <hi>finiſh their holy Courſe,</hi> and <hi>win the Crown of Righteouſneſs.</hi> What then? Why then you do bind his <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> hand and foot; and it is odds but you caſt out his <hi>deſpairing Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit.</hi> To be ſure you ſilence him; and very probably, you make him by and by to ſpeak <hi>Evangelically.</hi> And to fall to chiding of his <hi>legal</hi> ſelf; and counſelling it in <hi>Davids</hi>
                           <pb n="49" facs="tcp:39192:31"/>Rhetorick. <hi>Why caſt down O my Soul, why diſquieted in me? Truſt in God. For I, even I, may yet Praiſe him who is the health of my countenance and my God.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And now I ask. Should ſuch a <hi>Tower of David,</hi> ſuch an <hi>Armory</hi> as this; <hi>whereon there hang a thouſand bucklers and ſhields,</hi> for tempted de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpondent Souls; ſhould ſuch a practice ſuffer diſuſe? It would be unſpeakable loſs to the <hi>whole gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of the righteous.</hi> But, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be his excellent name; He that delights of <hi>bruiſed Reeds,</hi> to make <hi>poliſhed Pillars,</hi> in his Temple; and of <hi>ſmoaking flax</hi> to make <hi>burning and ſhining lights;</hi> He is more <hi>wiſe</hi> and <hi>kind</hi> than to admit it. <hi>Glory be to him in the higheſt.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="reason">
                        <p>
                           <label>R. 3.</label> 
                           <hi>This practice doubles the glory of God, from the Faith and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation of Saints deceaſed.</hi> If I may ſo ſpeak, God had from themſelves <hi>one crop,</hi> Or <hi>tribute</hi> of glory. And would have had it, tho' no eye but
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:39192:32"/>his own, had ſeen their Faith and Converſation. Tho' no mortal man had obſerved and followed them. But <hi>now, now</hi> that Faith and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation are not buried in Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livion; but <hi>are lifted up, and draw men after them;</hi> behold a <hi>ſecond crop,</hi> another <hi>tribute</hi> ſprings up! So fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful do living Chriſtian's Meditation and Imitation make them, that it may be ſaid of deceaſed ones, much like as of <hi>Sampſon.</hi> The Praiſes they bring unto their God in their <hi>death,</hi> be more than they which they brought in their <hi>life.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Can therefore any Lover of God, be without a deep ſenſe, of the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this practice? Or need to be farther told; that he who hath <hi>made all things for his glory,</hi> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired this practice for the ſame? Here I muſt believe that <hi>none are</hi> Blind, but thoſe that <hi>will</hi> not ſee.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="reason">
                        <p>
                           <label>R. 4.</label> 
                           <hi>This Practice doth likewiſe add unto the joy of Saints deceaſed.</hi> Heaven, is the element of Joy.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:39192:32"/>There's leſs water in the <hi>Sea,</hi> and light in the <hi>Sun,</hi> than Joy in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. But we are generally taught, that the Inhabitants have <hi>various</hi> degrees; even after the <hi>Reſurrection.</hi> However it be, it is this only that I would here propoſe: <hi>viz.</hi> Of their Joys in Heaven this muſt needs be <hi>one,</hi> that they did <hi>in their meaſure,</hi> glorifie God in their day upon Earth. And, if they have knowledge of it; it muſt be another Joy, to have their Faith and Obedience <hi>live,</hi> and <hi>bear fruit, after that they are tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>planted.</hi> To have their old <hi>Graces</hi> and <hi>Duties,</hi> for many years after, to <hi>edify their Brethren</hi> and <hi>glorifie their Father.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>And why we may not conceive them <hi>ſoon to know it,</hi> when it is ſo; let them ſay that can! I cannot. With humble ſubmiſſion, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that they are informed of it, when the matter of their Joy is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained. Whether the <hi>holy Angels give them notices;</hi> or what way they
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:39192:33"/>receive the ſame, I take not on me to determine. Some have thought, that this is true concerning men Damned. Such whoſe <hi>Errors</hi> are remembred to the <hi>diffuſing</hi> of their enmity and malignity, after their death; they have proportionable encreaſes of their torment in Hell made, <hi>preſently</hi> made; and with full ſignifications given of the meritori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly procuring cauſe of it. And on the other ſide, concerning Saints in Heaven, ſome have preſumed this, <hi>viz.</hi> That ſuch whoſe <hi>Faith and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Life,</hi> are commemorated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> made uſe of to the edification of the Church; they receive like encreaſes of Joy. As <hi>ſoon made,</hi> as the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid ſinners increaſes of Torment. Learned men have thought, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.10. to make this way. <hi>I the Lord ſearch the heart, I try the reins, even to give to every man ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his ways, and according to the FRUIT of his doings;</hi> and with full certification of the ſervice that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:39192:33"/>is ſo, of grace, rewarded,</p>
                        <p>I contend not, but, to as many as, with me, do ſuppoſe this; (which I think no one will pretend an abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to diſprove;) To ſuch at leaſt I ſhall think this reaſon of good force. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the very ſingle account hereof, I dare ask them, <hi>Is there not a cauſe for the commended Practice?</hi> If we on Earth have <hi>Power,</hi> ſhould we not have <hi>Will,</hi> to add to the Joy of our Brethren in Heaven.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="reason">
                        <p>
                           <label>R. 5.</label> 
                           <hi>This Practice of good men, exalts the ſaving grace of God.</hi> Grace un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a <hi>Sinner,</hi> is, and will be an <hi>eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Wonder.</hi> Saving grace, even moſt reſtrainedly conſidered, is <hi>above all</hi> the bleſſing and praiſe that can be given it, in the very ſtate of Glory. <hi>Abraham</hi> himſelf, even after the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, will be unableadequate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to praiſe the grace of <hi>his own</hi> Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation. The grace that took him out of his <hi>miſery,</hi> and qualified him and brought him unto <hi>Glory.</hi> That ſaid to him in his blood, <hi>Live.</hi> That
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:39192:34"/>when he was alive, gave him <hi>Life more abundantly.</hi> And when he wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>Meet,</hi> placed him in <hi>the inheritan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> of the Saints in Light.</hi> This grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> unto his <hi>ſingle Perſon,</hi> will tranſcen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> all his <hi>poſſible</hi> conception. But le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> this Grace to him, be conſidered i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> its juſt <hi>extent.</hi> As <hi>ſaving</hi> him, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> making him an <hi>Inſtrument</hi> of ſavin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>many</hi> others. In a ſenſe, the <hi>Fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> of thouſands of heirs of Salvation An <hi>Exemplar</hi> unto them. Making his Faith and Obedience, bleſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> means of grace, unto multitude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Cauſing <hi>generations to call him bleſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> Uſing him, when Alive, and al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> when Dead, as a <hi>Co-worker with Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>
                           </hi> What an addition is this? Thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> that <hi>makes Salvation it ſelf ſomewh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> more than it ſelf.</hi> Yea much more. As to ſave a man from death at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Gallows, and to make a King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> him, is much. But to proceed an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> to make him the means, of raiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> many others unto Thrones is ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> much more.</p>
                        <pb n="55" facs="tcp:39192:34"/>
                        <p>In a word then. Who can won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that the Grace of God hath choſe this method! And engaged us to conſider and imitate, the grace of our Friends departed. <hi>His good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs is above the Heavens.</hi> And the effects of it, muſt be like unto it. Therefore he beſtows not Salvation <hi>paſſive,</hi> without <hi>Active:</hi> that is, whom he <hi>ſaves,</hi> he alſo makes (inſtrumentally) <hi>Saviours.</hi> And why! but becauſe he will praiſe his grace, and make it like itſelf. And ſo be <hi>Glorifyed in his Saints, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mired in all them that do Believe.</hi> He will leave nothing to be ſaid that it <hi>might have been done</hi> for them, that was not done.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="reason">
                        <p>
                           <label>R. 6.</label> 
                           <hi>This Practice is unto all the living, a charm of great ſweetneſs to moſt exemplary Faith and Holineſs:</hi> For what heart will not ſtrain for the <hi>pureſt</hi> faith and <hi>moſt unſpotted</hi> Life, upon the conſideration that God intends it for a <hi>Pattern.</hi> And commands all its good, to be eyed
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:39192:35"/>and imitated. who will or can ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gue otherwiſe! I am to be a <hi>Copy.</hi> I will therefore write <hi>fair, as for my Life;</hi> and <hi>beware of blots and blurs.</hi> I am to be a <hi>Guide,</hi> and be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. I will therefore make <hi>ſtraight paths to my feet;</hi> and dread a <hi>falſe ſtep</hi> in <hi>Doctrine</hi> or <hi>Manners.</hi> I am <hi>to ſpeak even when I am dead.</hi> I will therefore <hi>ſeaſon with ſalt every word.</hi> And ſee with great carefulneſs, that none be found <hi>hurtful,</hi> or <hi>uſeleſs.</hi> If Poſterity <hi>follow me,</hi> they ſhall <hi>follow Chriſt.</hi> If they <hi>walk as I,</hi> I will ſee they ſhall <hi>walk as He walked.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>A ſweet and ſalutary Reaſoning; is it not! And who would have been, without ſuch a <hi>Charm!</hi> If any pretend to be <hi>ſo ſpiritual,</hi> that they can <hi>perfect holineſs</hi> without it; and therefore give God no thanks for it; to ſpeak the mildeſt thing that can be ſaid, I think that a great <hi>Jealouſie of their ſtate, is Godly and Neceſſary.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Brevity</hi> commands me to offer no
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:39192:35"/>more than theſe few <hi>Inferences</hi> for application of this Truth. Diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed minds may eaſily farther apply it in their own thoughts, unto its obvious purpoſes.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 1.</label> 
                        <hi>What garments of praiſe are Faith and Holineſs!</hi> Surely incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable. Otherwiſe our <hi>Predeceſſors</hi> attire with them, needed not to be ſo obſerved, ſo followed. The <hi>Church i. e.</hi> holy believers, are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Bride</hi> beautifully decked. Their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Holy Life</hi> bear the names of <hi>Embroidery, Silk, Fine lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen, Silver, Gold,</hi> and <hi>Jewels.</hi> Yea, and are declared to be the <hi>End</hi> of our <hi>Saviours</hi> all-tranſcending Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs imputed unto us. They are therefore <hi>miſerably Blind,</hi> who are <hi>contentedly Naked.</hi> And as <hi>ſhamefully Naked,</hi> who are not <hi>thus cloathed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 2.</label> 
                        <hi>How many are our Miniſters more than the Earth bears!</hi> For all our <hi>fore-runners</hi> unto Heaven abide <hi>Miniſters</hi> ſtill unto us. Their <hi>faith</hi>
                        <pb n="58" facs="tcp:39192:36"/>and Holineſs, if we are not wanting to our ſelves, will be our daily <hi>Lectures.</hi> We have every day the refuſal of them. The King of the Church, for many reaſons aforeſaid, requires our uſe thereof. Who then dares ſay, <hi>that Miniſters be ſcarce!</hi> O that deaf <hi>Adders,</hi> and dull and ſlow Hearers of them, were ſo.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 3.</label> 
                        <hi>What need of Gods mercy have all his family on earth!</hi> All are bound to Remember and Imitate their Brethren in Heaven. Now it is Mercy very great, to be bound to a <hi>practice ſo beneficial, delightful,</hi> and <hi>honourable,</hi> as this hath been ſhewn to be. And of this mercy, who ſaith that he hath no need! again, 'tis mercy unſpeakable, to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>given the neglect of ſo gracious a <hi>Precept.</hi> Of ſo kind a <hi>Preſcription</hi> againſt ſin and ſorrow. And of this mercy, what an abundance do we all want? I ſay this upon good war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant; I am jealous that the genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:39192:36"/>of <hi>true Iſraelites</hi> do need a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al abundance. Being as to this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, guilty of above ordinary neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence. <hi>The Lord grant unto us that we may find mercy of the Lord in that day;</hi> (ſo the Apoſtle names the <hi>Judgment-day,</hi> tho' ſome critical Heads have conſtrued it of another.)</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 4.</label> 
                        <hi>How unexpectable is ſinleſs perfection in this World?</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Hence <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> 
                           <hi>looking off,</hi> from the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned witneſſes and patterns to a more perfect exemplar, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.2. Chriſt the <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, <hi>as endur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing — deſpiſing</hi> — and <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap> as now ſet down, and ſo having perfected his <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, and hence propoſed to the exerciſed as their example and encouragement, hence <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate or analogize your ſelves to him, as in <hi>ver.</hi> 3. Chriſt was indeed the Author—in an higher ſenſe, but here I think he is propoſed as the moſt perfect and encouraging exemplar of, thorough coſtly and ſucceſsful faithfulneſs.</note> The very <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had it not. And this reſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of our imitation unto their <hi>Faith,</hi> ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues that they had not. And implicite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tells us, that they had Errors of <hi>Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and <hi>Practice</hi> that we are to Decline, not
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:39192:37"/>to follow. In <hi>Writing</hi> the Holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> they <hi>had</hi> and <hi>profeſſed to have</hi> the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi>'s infallible gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance. But at other times, and to other <hi>purpoſes,</hi> they <hi>never had</hi> it, <hi>nor pretended to it.</hi> No, their own Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings record their <hi>Miſtakes</hi> and <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriages.</hi> Of the Saints of the <hi>Old Teſtament,</hi> there can be little matter of doubt concerning them, the ſame thing may be ſaid; and this only ſhall be added. The Holy Ghoſt commends them unto us indeed, for very <hi>uſeful witneſſes</hi> and <hi>patterns,</hi> as hath been before ſhewn, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12.1. But then, as in way of caution <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our Dreams of their Perfection,</hi> in the very next verſe what doth he? He bids us <hi>look off from them all,</hi> unto an incomparably more noble and truely perfect one, <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>. <hi>Looking off</hi> [from them] <hi>unto Jeſus the Author and Finiſher</hi> (or Leader and Perfector) <hi>of our Faith. Jeſus</hi> that had <hi>deſpiſed the ſhame, endured
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:39192:37"/>the Croſs, and received his bleſſed</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>or eſcape</hi> out of all his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings; <hi>having ſit down at Gods right hand.</hi> Unto this bleſſed <hi>Jeſus,</hi> in the next verſe we are inſtructed to <hi>proportionate</hi> our ſelves, as ſome think the Greek <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> to ſignify. Our Nature was ſinleſs under the Sun, in Jeſus Chriſt, but as to us <hi>meer men,</hi> it is truly ſaid, <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                           <hi>Adam</hi> loſt more Innocence and Purity in an <hi>hour,</hi> than his Poſterity will recover <hi>to the Worlds end.</hi>
                        </q>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 5.</label> 
                        <hi>What a reproachful thing, is Univerſal imitation of the beſt men!</hi> Their <hi>holy Faith</hi> and <hi>Life</hi> is all you are bid to follow. To Swallow their <hi>Errors,</hi> and practiſe their <hi>Sins,</hi> is what God and they themſelves forbid you. And is imitating or them in the things wherein they were not <hi>themſelves.</hi> But were more <hi>Satan</hi>'s, than their <hi>own men.</hi> Wherefore ſo to do is to comply with <hi>Satan,</hi> not to conform unto <hi>them.</hi> Let it alſo be conſidered;
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:39192:38"/>that to affect and ſtrain to take up their (unaffected) <hi>Tones, Geſtures, Garbs,</hi> &amp;c. is to but ape their <hi>Huma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> it ſelf. And nothing of an imitation of their <hi>Piety.</hi> In <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> it is playfulneſs; in <hi>Men</hi> it's Childiſhneſs, if no worſe.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="doctrine">
                  <head>
                     <hi>D. 3.</hi> Conſideration of deceaſed Miniſters and Friends eſcape, out of all their ſublunary Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, is a neceſſary motive to the imitation of their Faith and Life.</head>
                  <p>The Original word <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> which we render <hi>End,</hi> is rendered an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcape,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.13. Nor doth it expreſs a meer <hi>End</hi> or common <hi>Iſſue</hi> of things. But an <hi>End atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with Victory, and deliverance out of things grievous.</hi> That the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of Saints that are bleſſed with ſuch an end, is as it is here aſſerted; is by the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> plainly declared. Who maketh it the <hi>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> unto the imitation that we have
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:39192:38"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ready preſſed. His words do evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently import as much as if he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>id theſe following ones. <q rend="margDblQuotes">Sirs, it is a <hi>hot ſervice</hi> I put you upon. Imitation of departed Saints <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Holineſs,</hi> is no eaſie buſineſs. <hi>African Lyons</hi> appear in every ſtep of it's way. All the <hi>World</hi> is in arms againſt it. Throwing <hi>Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brands, Arrows,</hi> and <hi>Death.</hi> The <hi>Devil</hi> and <hi>his Angels</hi> raiſe their <hi>Poſſe,</hi> and do their <hi>worſt.</hi> I know your <hi>want,</hi> and God directs me to furniſh you with a moſt <hi>power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi> Encouragement. One, which if you rightly uſe, you ſhall walk undauntedly in your moſt difficult Duty. You ſhall <hi>Run,</hi> and not <hi>faint.</hi> The <hi>Swords</hi> of them that <hi>lay</hi> at you, ſhall not hold; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther their <hi>Spears,</hi> nor their <hi>Darts.</hi> Their Arrows ſhall not make you flee. You ſhall laugh at the ſhak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their <hi>Spears.</hi> And this ſo mighty motive, is <hi>Conſideration.</hi> Careful and Curious Inſpection,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:39192:39"/>reiterated and repeated contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation. To wit of your Pred<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors glorious <hi>Conqueſts,</hi> over a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> that ſtands againſt you. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> their triumphant <hi>Ingreſs</hi> into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> caeleſtial and eternal Bleſſedneſs One too rich, to be comprehende<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> by the preſent poverty of your Underſtandings. But yet one whereof your little Underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is enough, both to ſweeten a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> the bitterneſs, and ſpoil the tempt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power of all the <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> of this world. <hi>Keep this conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and live; Keep it as the Apple of your Eye.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the diſplay of this general po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the weakeſt minds, I will caſt it's contents into theſe four par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="particular">
                     <p>
                        <label>P. 1.</label> 
                        <hi>Our deceaſed good Miniſters and Friends, were in this world threſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and winnowed as much as our ſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> are.</hi> Their <hi>Eſcape</hi> out of ſufferings ſpeaks their <hi>fore-endurance</hi> of them. Of which their Endurance, it will
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:39192:39"/>not be uſeleſs to take ſome good no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice. And ever and anon compare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>heir Hardſhips and our own. It <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s a ſmall <hi>Map,</hi> in which I muſt preſent the <hi>World</hi> of them.</p>
                     <p>Their Souls lodged in as <hi>Frail</hi> and as <hi>Burthenſom Bodies,</hi> as, ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily, ours do. And, as hard to keep in <hi>Subjection,</hi> and <hi>be poſſeſſed in Honour.</hi> Bodies that were as very <hi>Priſons</hi> and <hi>Fetters</hi> unto their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits. Whoſe <hi>Weakneſſes, Pains,</hi> and <hi>Deformities</hi> were neither few, nor light.</p>
                     <p>Their treatment by the <hi>World,</hi> was with the ſame malignity as ours is, or worſe. It <hi>Hated</hi> them as much; <hi>Cenſured, Reproached,</hi> and every way <hi>Injured</hi> them, by <hi>ſecret</hi> and <hi>open</hi> practices. One while it beſpake them, as it doth us, in words <hi>ſmooth as butter, ſweet as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny-combs.</hi> By the ſweet Poyſon of <hi>Flattery,</hi> deſigning upon them the worſt of cruelty. Aſſaying by the Lordly <hi>diſh</hi> and ſweet <hi>milk,</hi> to court
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:39192:40"/>them unto the fatal <hi>Nail</hi> and <hi>Ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer.</hi> Another time it ſpake of them as it doth of you, <hi>all manner of ev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Poured out <hi>Curſings and Bitterneſs</hi> breathed out <hi>threatnings</hi> and <hi>ſlaugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi> Trying if it were poſſible to <hi>frighten</hi> whom they could not <hi>flatter</hi> out of God's way.</p>
                     <p>Their <hi>Temptations by Satan,</hi> were no leſs than our own. Are we peſtred with his <hi>Suggeſtions, Perſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, Inſtigations?</hi> So were they, as they have oft complained unto ſome of <hi>us:</hi> and unto <hi>God,</hi> in the hearing of all that worſhipped with them. Do we find that he ſubtilly ſuits his temptations unto our <hi>Ages,</hi> our <hi>Tempers,</hi> and our <hi>Conditions</hi> in the World? We are vain if we think he did otherwiſe with them. Doth he aſſault us oft-times in temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations <hi>unto ſins, from which we think our ſelves moſt ſafe?</hi> No queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on but he ſo aſſaulted them. In a word; All his Logical <hi>fallacies,</hi> all his Politick <hi>wiles,</hi> all his Military
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:39192:40"/>
                        <hi>ſtratagems,</hi> were uſed againſt them as ſurely as they are againſt us. How many have told us their Temptations unto <hi>Atheiſm, Blaſphemy, Deſpair, Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Self-murther,</hi> and what not?</p>
                     <p>Their <hi>Afflictions from God,</hi> were ſuch as ours do not appear to exceed. Underſtand me of Afflictions upon <hi>Soul, Body, Name, Eſtate, Family, Friends.</hi> From his hand are all; are they not? By whomſoever they are <hi>Executed</hi> 'tis by him they are <hi>Order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</hi> And that as to the <hi>Sort, Degree,</hi> and <hi>Duration</hi> of them. Now, can you anſwer me? Which of your <hi>Souls</hi> doth God exerciſe with more <hi>Griefs, Fears,</hi> &amp; <hi>Anguiſh</hi> than he did theirs? Who of you have <hi>Bodies</hi> more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the <hi>Stone, Colick,</hi> and <hi>Strangury, Feaver, Conſumption,</hi> and <hi>Palſie,</hi> than theirs were? Who can ſay his <hi>Name</hi> is more Laden with reproach, than their <hi>Names</hi> uſed to be? Or that his <hi>Eſtate</hi> hath been ſo torn from him, as none of theirs ever was. Or, that <hi>Providence</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:39192:41"/>made any of their <hi>Families</hi> ſuch Hoſpitals, as it hath made his. Or ſo parted any of them from their <hi>Lovers</hi> and <hi>Friends,</hi> as it hath part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him. <hi>Many</hi> indeed <hi>are the affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the righteous in this World.</hi> But not more than thoſe of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous before you, were, who are aſcended into the World where none are.</p>
                     <p>Their <hi>Indwelling Sin,</hi> was their perpetual troubler, as ours is. And found them as much to do, as ours findeth us. Held them in <hi>continual warfare,</hi> as ours holdeth us. They all had Sin, and felt Sin, and lament<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Sin, in all and every part of them. As <hi>wormwood</hi> hath bitterneſs in its <hi>Root,</hi> in its <hi>Stalk,</hi> and in its <hi>Leaves.</hi> Their <hi>Minds</hi> had abiding Unteach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ableneſs; <hi>Wills,</hi> Untractableneſs; <hi>Conſciences,</hi> Unſenſibleneſs; <hi>Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> Unfaithfulneſs; <hi>Affections,</hi> Unorderlineſs; <hi>Imaginations,</hi> Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulineſs. That which came into them, when their Souls came into
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:39192:41"/>their Bodies, never perfectly left them till their ſouls left their Bodies. All days of their lives therefore, their <hi>Faith</hi> was weak, <hi>Hope</hi> infirm, <hi>Love</hi> chill. Many a trembling hour they ſpent, in fear that they were but ſhadows and empty ſhows of Faith, and Hope, and Love, that they had. In fear of their being Graceleſs; yea (and what is worſe) <hi>paſt the day of Grace.</hi> Being <hi>Unrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled</hi> to God, yea, and (thro' dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delay,) <hi>Unreconcilable.</hi> Many have ſo feared; and all have lived exclaiming, <hi>O wretched Man that I am who ſhall deliver me!</hi> Such fears, ſimple ſouls do think to have been no ones <hi>bitter Draughts</hi> but their own. But I tell them, they cannot anſwer me this queſtion: <hi>To which of your friends in Heaven can you turn, that hath not drank them!</hi> Again,</p>
                     <p>Their Loads of <hi>Actual Sin</hi> preſſed them down, as ſorely as ours do preſs us. <hi>My ſin is ever before me,</hi> was the perpetual cry of one of them.
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:39192:42"/>Are we Burthened with our <hi>ſins,</hi> their <hi>Aggravations,</hi> and th ir <hi>Deme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits!</hi> they were ſo, with theirs. Their ſins againſt <hi>Law,</hi> againſt <hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> againſt <hi>Conſcience.</hi> With their Aggravations by their <hi>Multitudes,</hi> their <hi>Kinds,</hi> and their <hi>Circumſtances.</hi> With their Demerits of <hi>outward;</hi> of <hi>inward,</hi> and of <hi>eternal</hi> and <hi>extremeſt</hi> puniſhments. For theſe, God knows what were their <hi>ſighs,</hi> and their <hi>groanings</hi> were not hid from Him.</p>
                     <p>Their <hi>mixtures of ſin</hi> in all <hi>Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral, Civil,</hi> and <hi>Religious</hi> things, did foul their faces with weeping. Think you that it is a peculiar ſin, or grief of yours; in a great degree to <hi>Eat,</hi> &amp; <hi>Drink,</hi> to <hi>Buy</hi> and <hi>Sell,</hi> yea to uſe the holy <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> from <hi>ſelfiſh Principles</hi> and to <hi>ſelfiſh Ends;</hi> not Purely <hi>from Principles,</hi> and <hi>unto Ends Heavenly!</hi> your miſtake is groſs. It was the common ſin of all your friends in Heaven; and the common grief of all while they lived upon
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:39192:42"/>Earth. Ardently all <hi>deſired;</hi> but no one ever <hi>attained</hi> unto ſinleſs pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity; no, not in any one of their pathes, <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.12, 13. 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.8. <hi>Jam.</hi> 3.1. In every motion of <hi>Nature</hi> there was much of <hi>Corruption.</hi> In every Secular thing moſt <hi>lawful,</hi> there was what was <hi>Unlawful,</hi> In all <hi>holy things,</hi> there were <hi>Iniquities.</hi> And for theſe, went they mourning all their days.</p>
                     <p>Their long <hi>unaccompliſhed deſires,</hi> and <hi>unanſwered Prayers,</hi> made their hearts ſick an hundred times. Ours, be a <hi>ſword in our Bones,</hi> that we are prone to think did never cut any other Souls. But it is without any colour of Reaſon, that we think ſo in our haſte. It is very well known, God uſed to make our Predeceſſors wait, as long as He makes any of us. And as frequently they cryed, as we do now cry, <hi>How long wilt thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get me, O Lord, for ever? Mine eyes fail while I wait for my God. I am weary of my crying, my throat is dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:39192:43"/>For day and night thy hand is heavy upon me. O God, I cry in the day time, and thou heareſt not.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To conclude this particular; <hi>The ſorrows of death</hi> compaſſed them, as they compaſs us. Great was their <hi>conſternation,</hi> in the proſpect of their <hi>Diſſolution!</hi> Unto which, all their great <hi>Grace</hi> could not reconcile their reluctant <hi>Nature.</hi> With fearfulneſs and trembling they felt the <hi>King of Terrors</hi> entring, and pulling down their Tabernacle of Clay. Laying their <hi>Earthly Houſe</hi> in the Duſt. Turning their Fleſh into rottenneſs, and ſending it out of the ſight of man into darkneſs. Have we our <hi>terrors?</hi> they were not without theirs! Of ſome, and thoſe extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily ſanctified, it is credibly reported; that very <hi>Fear</hi> was their <hi>Executioner.</hi> And they died for fear of Death. Of others, I pray be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>think your ſelves; how was it that you ſaw them lye gaſping on their Beds? and heard them ratling in
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:39192:43"/>their Throats? and obſerved them to take the breach of the ſtrings of their <hi>Eyes</hi> and <hi>Heart?</hi> 'Tis impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble here to ſay all; and hard to me, not to ſay too much. But I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="particular">
                     <p>
                        <label>P. 2.</label> 
                        <hi>Theſe very Souls thus win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowed, are gloriouſly eſcaped out of all theſe evils.</hi> So the Text ſaith, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly. And ſo the whole Scripture, ſo brightly, that all are <hi>Believers</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſuch as are not <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> To quote the <hi>obvious Texts,</hi> would be to recite a great part of the <hi>Bible.</hi> Let that one which I produce recall others unto your remembrance. <hi>Rev.</hi> 14.13. <hi>Bleſſed are the dead that die in the Lord.</hi> An illuſtrious Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im! in few words declaring, man's great <hi>End</hi> or <hi>Aim;</hi> which is <hi>bleſſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> And man's only <hi>way unto the ſame;</hi> which is by <hi>dying in the Lord,</hi> or in <hi>the Faith of Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> after living in him by Faith. This Max<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im, St. <hi>John</hi> had from Heaven. And this he was bid to write, for the uſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:39192:44"/>of the Saints on Earth. And this he telleth us, is confirmed by the Holy Ghoſt. <hi>Yea, ſaith the Spirit, that they may reſt from their labours, and their works do follow them.</hi> In which confirmatory reaſons, we have theſe things aſſerted. <hi>ſcil.</hi> 1. That <hi>before their death in the Lord, theſe Saints had labours, and works for him which were hard.</hi> Such, as to be exempted from, was a part of bleſſedneſs. 2. That <hi>at their Death they were exempted from them.</hi> And now lived no more in <hi>Sweat,</hi> much leſs in <hi>Tears.</hi> 3. That <hi>with freedom from ſufferings they now received Gods Rewards of their Obedience.</hi> His re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of Grace, which are like the <hi>Donor;</hi> beyond comprehenſion, and objects of eternal wonder. Their works do follow them. That is, the <hi>immenſe</hi> reward of their <hi>ſlender</hi> work. The <hi>eternal</hi> reward of their <hi>ſhort</hi> work. <hi>The far more exceeding and eternal weight of Glory!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This argument <hi>flows with Milk
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:39192:44"/>and Honey;</hi> ſtay we and feed a while hereon. Think pleaſantly of what is proved ſo evidently. Saints, raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out of the <hi>Valley of Tears,</hi> are lift<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up into the <hi>Mount of Joy.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in no <hi>Eye</hi> ever wept, or <hi>Breaſt</hi> ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or <hi>Tongue</hi> complained. Or ever had <hi>cauſe</hi> or <hi>occaſion</hi> ſo to do. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, neither the <hi>World,</hi> nor the <hi>God of this World</hi> could ever give trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. For <hi>Satan's Vaſſals</hi> cannot reach it. And <hi>he and his Angels</hi> were long ago caſt far enough from it. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, the Immortal Father never gave a <hi>blow</hi> to any Child; or took from any the <hi>Kiſſes</hi> of his Mouth, ſweeter than Wine. Wherein <hi>ſin,</hi> the moſt hateful evil, hath no more place than the <hi>Devil,</hi> whoſe work it is. But the perfect purity long deſired, is fully enjoyed. Wherein, no one <hi>ſinful,</hi> or <hi>mixed</hi> and <hi>imperfect act,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver blemiſhed the holy <hi>ſtate.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>no Hope is ever delayed one minute;</hi> nor ought is <hi>deſired,</hi> before God's will is that it ſhould be <hi>poſſeſſed.</hi>
                        <pb n="76" facs="tcp:39192:45"/>Wherein there is no <hi>Doubt,</hi> or <hi>Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance</hi> of Life; nor any <hi>Fear,</hi> or <hi>Poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility</hi> of Death. Wherein, we do all know, all things are better than any of us upon Earth can know.</p>
                     <p>For we know, that when Saints enter the <hi>Houſe</hi> made without hands, they preſently take poſſeſſion of all the <hi>Goods.</hi> And who can know, till he goes up and ſees, how <hi>many</hi> and how <hi>rich</hi> they be? Indeed the holy Oracles, do warrant thus much to be ſaid of our good Friends that are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred there.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>They poſſeſs bleſſed Light,</hi> One, in compariſon whereof, their former knowledge was but a leſs thick dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. The open light of the Sun, vaſtly exceeds a few Beams ſtrained through the crevice of a Wall. And no leſs doth <hi>Gods manifeſtation</hi> of himſelf above, exceed that which he affords his Church below. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is there any compare between the ſtrength of a glorified <hi>Eye,</hi> and of an imperfectly ſanctified one. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:39192:45"/>glorified ones, the deep Fountains of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Grace</hi> are laid open. The riches of Goodneſs, the beauties of Holineſs, the glories of Power are <hi>manifeſted.</hi> The Embroideries of <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence</hi> are unfolded. 'Tis not eaſie to name, what God doth hide from 'em. For why? He himſelf is <hi>All in all.</hi> And, this we know, <hi>They do ſee him as he is!</hi> Wherefore neceſſarily,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>They poſſeſs bleſſed Love.</hi> So ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gues the infallible Teacher. <hi>We ſhall be like him; For we ſhall ſee him.</hi> God is love. And ſight of God, turns us into flames of Love. Such are our glorified Friends, like unto the bleſſed Angels. Ever <hi>receiving</hi> the higheſt love, that God confers on finite Creatures; and <hi>giving</hi> back the greateſt love, that God can have from their glorified Powers. Upon earth, the Fire of their Love was a little <hi>Spark;</hi> it is now a <hi>Mount.</hi> That ſpark, (as Kitchen-fire,) often languiſhed; almoſt expired, for want of feeding by proper Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations But in their preſent Mount of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:39192:46"/>Celeſtial fire, there is no <hi>variableneſs or ſhadow of change.</hi> The Divine glory ſo holds their Eyes, and heats their Hearts. So, that their <hi>ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moring Thoughts</hi> are never interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and their <hi>enflamed Affections</hi> ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver abated. Certainly therefore,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>They poſſeſs bleſſed Life. Valere, vita eſt.</hi> To be Alive, is to be in fulneſs of Joy. And where is that fulneſs but in Love? <hi>Where is Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter if not in the Sea? Where is Light if not in the Sun? Where is Joy if not in Love. Light</hi> doth not more na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turally kindle ſacred <hi>Love,</hi> than <hi>Love</hi> creates ſupream <hi>Joy.</hi> For what can there be leſs than all De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, where there is nothing but <hi>Love;</hi> and that, as this is, without <hi>Diminution</hi> or <hi>End.</hi> It is ſure, that our Friends Live in the <hi>Triumphs of Joy,</hi> if they live in the <hi>Sunſhines of Knowledge,</hi> and <hi>Flames of Love.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>True it is, <hi>great is the number</hi> of them that dwell in this <hi>Light, Love,</hi> and <hi>Life.</hi> Tho comparatively <hi>few are ſaved;</hi> the <hi>City that is above,</hi> is
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:39192:46"/>Populous, but the multitude of its Citizens, doth not <hi>Impoveriſh,</hi> but <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Adorn</hi> it. For why? GOD is its Treaſure. And good INFINITE is not by any num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers <hi>exhauſted</hi> or <hi>leſſened.</hi> The Sun's light is but finite. Yet all men enjoy the light of it; and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one, as ſufficiently, as if no ones Eyes but his own received it. God is Infinite. And much more may all his Favourites above enjoy Him: every one as <hi>fully,</hi> as if he enjoyed him only.</p>
                     <p>Be it added; Earthly excellencies are all of them, like to rich Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes. By Cuſtom they wax leſs <hi>ſenſible,</hi> at leaſt leſs <hi>grateful,</hi> to ſuch as carry them. And ceaſe to be <hi>ſweet,</hi> when they ceaſe to be <hi>New.</hi> But it is not ſo with Excellencies heavenly. God's own happineſs is now as pleaſant unto Him, as it was millions of ages agone. It was never at all <hi>New,</hi> but ever <hi>moſt ſweet.</hi> And he has provided his Children
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:39192:47"/>alſo a <hi>Felicity,</hi> that ſhall not need to be commended by <hi>Novelty.</hi> One that ſhall reliſh as well with them to <hi>eternal ages</hi> as at the <hi>firſt moment.</hi> Which we cannot doubt, if we do not forget this: <hi>viz.</hi> That Heavenly Joy is <hi>Perfect.</hi> And what is Perfect, is indeficient; never <hi>abates;</hi> never can <hi>Die,</hi> or be <hi>Sick,</hi> or be <hi>weaker</hi> at one time than at another. Things of limited goodneſs, admit change and wearineſs of them. It being neceſſary to leave one for another. Yea, and having in them ſomewhat that is <hi>hurtful</hi> too, and not <hi>delicious,</hi> no wonder if they ſometimes become nauſeous. But good that is <hi>unbound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> and reaches to the ſatisfaction of all our Deſires; and is <hi>unmixed,</hi> and miniſters nothing beſide delights; ſuch as the Heavenly good is; this muſt alway taſte alike. Unto the ſweetneſs of this <hi>nothing can be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded:</hi> nor <hi>can any thing be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way</hi> from it.</p>
                     <p>Well; this, and more than this,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:39192:47"/>is the bleſſed ſtate of our godly Friends deceaſed. A ſtate, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of every <hi>Poſſeſſor</hi> lives in moſt <hi>deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious</hi> and <hi>eternal Rapture,</hi> Heaven is it ſelf; and they we ſpeak of are in Heaven. But concerning both, it muſt be ſaid, <hi>'tis but a little portion of them that is heard! The one half is not told us.</hi> Nor doth it <hi>yet appear,</hi> ſave very imperfectly, what they are. As to that which through Gods grace doth appear, it follows in our next particular.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="particular">
                     <p>
                        <label>P. 3.</label> 
                        <hi>Their glorious Eſcape unto Heaven ought to be well Conſidered by as on Earth.</hi> The word of command is in the text. And is a very re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable one, uſed but once more in all the <hi>New Teſtament, viz. Act.</hi> 17.23. where it is put to expreſs the careful and ſevere conſideration, that the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> took of the <hi>Athenians</hi> Devotion. In minds not atheiſtical, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>here muſt needs be ever and anon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ome occaſional Thoughts bubling <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>p. But they are bubbles indeed,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:39192:48"/>that ſignifie <hi>little</hi> and effect <hi>nothing.</hi> They make not that <hi>Conſideration</hi> which is here demanded. Which conſiſts in <hi>much</hi> and <hi>ſerious</hi> ſpeech with our ſelves concerning the Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of our godly Friends. <hi>Streams,</hi> fed by a <hi>living Spring,</hi> flow conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly; and do <hi>enrich</hi> and <hi>give delight</hi> where they come. And ſuch are the <hi>Thoughts</hi> and <hi>Soliloquies,</hi> which do ever much better our <hi>Hearts</hi> and our <hi>Ways.</hi> Such as flow from a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal <hi>Principle</hi> and <hi>Diſpoſition;</hi> and are maintained daily by the ſame. Even without thoſe <hi>outward occaſions</hi> of them, with which ſlight and tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſient thoughts do flow and ebb; or rather dry away.</p>
                     <p>Fix it in your minds, that it is the Will of God, that is here decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo to be. That he requireth you to have this ſaid <hi>glorious Victory</hi> much in your minds. That your <hi>Thoughtfulneſs</hi> of it will truly pleaſe Him. And your <hi>Forgetfulneſs</hi> and <hi>Neglect,</hi> incenſe him. Let your
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:39192:48"/>Wills ſubmit to this acknowledged Will of God; and command <hi>all that is within you</hi> ſo to do. Become you <hi>Convinced</hi> of your duty herein; and <hi>Diſpoſed</hi> to do it. You ſhall then find within you a <hi>Fountain,</hi> whence <hi>numerous, delicious,</hi> and <hi>efficacious</hi> Thoughts, ſhall ſpring. <hi>Your own reins ſhall inſtruct you</hi> daily. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out other <hi>Monitors,</hi> (the Holy <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit</hi> excepted,) it ſhall become of your daily <hi>Buſineſs</hi> and <hi>Recreation</hi> alſo, to conſider the Conqueſt forepraiſed. Without <hi>other calls,</hi> your minds will run to it, and on it. They will be often ſpeaking, to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, each of them.</p>
                     <p>Here am I, <hi>in my paſſage</hi> through the <hi>red ſea; Hope</hi> and <hi>Fear</hi> divide my Life. <hi>Hope</hi> of Eſcaping, <hi>Fear</hi> of Drowning. Eſcaping as an <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelite;</hi> Drowning, as an <hi>Egyptian.</hi> O ye my godly Miniſters and Friends that are ſweetly got aſhore, I cannot but think of you. Of your ſafe <hi>Landing;</hi> and joyful <hi>Reception</hi> above.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:39192:49"/>Methinks I hear you recounting your old <hi>Weakneſſes, Fears,</hi> and <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</hi> And wondring at the <hi>arm of Grace</hi> that carried you through them. Rejoycing in the change you feel. Triumphing over <hi>Sin, Satan,</hi> and the <hi>World,</hi> that withſtood you. And ſaying, how little danger the <hi>Sea</hi> hath, if the true <hi>Pilot</hi> be but duly truſted. How ſafely all muſt go, and how ſweetly all muſt end. How reaſonable is it for all he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth, to truſt him in the <hi>worſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> ſtorms.</hi> To bear moſt patiently eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Difficulty;</hi> being they are but for a moment, and their reward is Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of exceeding weight. How you would have even gloried in all your <hi>Tribulations,</hi> had you but known the ten thouſandth part of what you now ſee. How you would adviſe us that be ſtill on the Sea, were you to ſpeak with us. What you would tell your Followers of <hi>Sins folly,</hi> the <hi>Creatures vanity, Gods bounty, Chriſts excellency, Holineſs its beauty:</hi> (Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:39192:49"/>of <hi>State,</hi> of <hi>Heart,</hi> of <hi>Life.</hi>) O what a deal would you tell, that do know now what a <hi>Rewarder</hi> God is? Of all, that <hi>in patient continuance in well-doing, do ſeek and ſerve him.</hi> You would make us all aſhamed of our ſelves. <hi>Miniſters</hi> of their Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching; <hi>People</hi> of their Hearing; <hi>Both,</hi> of their worſe living.</p>
                     <p>O ye bleſſed Spirits, and not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Healed,</hi> but <hi>Beautified.</hi> Often have I heard you complain of <hi>Wounds, Bruiſes,</hi> and <hi>Putrifying ſores</hi> like my own. And now methinks I ſee you without <hi>Spot</hi> or <hi>Wrinkle</hi> or <hi>any ſuch thing.</hi> While the cure of my own Diſeaſes, is little more than begun: In you, in you it is, that I read the high Praiſes of Chriſt your <hi>Phyſician</hi> and mine. Should I let go the memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of <hi>you,</hi> I ſhould leſſen the Honour of <hi>Him.</hi> In you it is that I read the praiſes of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Then it is he appears to me a moſt wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Builder,</hi> when I look on you his moſt glorious <hi>Temples.</hi> Then I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:39192:50"/>ſure he is able to raiſe me alſo out of my ruins.</p>
                     <p>O ye Conquerors and more than <hi>Conquerors;</hi> whom I knew when you were <hi>Warriours.</hi> And under my own hardſhips of <hi>warfare.</hi> My own, who was your unworthy Fellow-Souldier under Chriſt's Banner. How congra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulate I your <hi>Conqueſts</hi> and <hi>Triumphs?</hi> How admire I the <hi>Truth, Power</hi> and <hi>Love</hi> of your and my <hi>Captain?</hi> How uneaſie doth the ſight of your Crowns make me, till I am with you, and like you? If I forget you, O ye Angels-fellows, <hi>let my Tongue cleave to the roof of my Mouth!</hi> If mine Eye keep poring always upon my SEA, my SICKNESS and my WARFARE; if it be not alſo turned on your PASSAGE, your CURE, and your CONQUEST, <hi>let my Arm fall from my Shoulder-blade!</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The (<gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap>,) Contempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors of the bleſſed End of godly Friends, are Chriſtians that thus converſe with themſelves. I ſay
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:39192:50"/>thus, unto the true <hi>end</hi> and <hi>uſe</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. And unto this end do <hi>converſe</hi> or <hi>conſider,</hi> not <hi>tranſiently think.</hi> There is a great difference between a <hi>ſtep</hi> and a <hi>walk.</hi> And there is no leſs, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween a <hi>thought</hi> and a <hi>conſideration.</hi> I come therefore to the laſt particular.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="particular">
                     <p>
                        <label>P. 4.</label> 
                        <hi>This conſideration of godly Friends eſcápe unto Heaven, is a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive moſt neceſſary, unto imitation of their Faith and Holineſs.</hi> The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles uſe of it as ſuch, proves it ſuch. But, to give meaſure preſſed down and running over, it ſhall be add<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. (1.) <hi>The beſt of Chriſtians, do need motive Conſiderations.</hi> Which is acknowledged by all that are ſo much as titularly Chriſtians. (2.) <hi>Of motive Conſiderations, this is of the beſt.</hi> Which will appear from the natural effects of it, in which its motive virtue is moſt reſplendent. Of theſe, the ſeven following ones, are not the leaſt principal.</p>
                     <div n="1" type="effect">
                        <p>
                           <label>E. 1.</label> 
                           <hi>This Conſideration confirms our Faith.</hi> Our Faith of the holy God's
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:39192:51"/>bountifulneſs, and of holy men's bleſſedneſs. It is true, that the <hi>H. Spirit's Light</hi> diſpels our darkneſs, and enlightens our minds. And, he giveth us the <hi>Goſpel</hi> for a <hi>Lamp;</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> for an <hi>Eye.</hi> But can any man doubt it? The <hi>Goſpel</hi> is cleared and <hi>Faith</hi> ſtrengthned more than a little, by <hi>Examples.</hi> Examples of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed goodneſs of God to Men, and the bleſſedneſs of men in that good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of God. Eſpecially by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Perſons <hi>known, and dear unto our ſelves.</hi> Put the caſe you know and believe ever ſo well of a <hi>Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cian.</hi> Yet let him once make per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Cures on many of your moſt dangerouſly diſeaſed Relations: Your confidence of <hi>his ability,</hi> and his <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients ſafety</hi> will be encreaſed. You will be ſomewhat more fearleſs to truſt him with your own Life, than you were before. The Application is eaſie.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="effect">
                        <p>
                           <label>E. 2.</label> 
                           <hi>This Conſideration raiſes our Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions.</hi> Our Apprehenſions and
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:39192:51"/>Eſtimations of <hi>God,</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of the <hi>H. Spirit,</hi> and of the <hi>Goſpel-Covenant.</hi> You cannot ſee your dear Friends ſaved by them, but you muſt the more <hi>eſteem</hi> and <hi>value</hi> them! Their ſo great Salvation, that <hi>certifies the goodneſs</hi> of the Efficients and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments unto you, muſt needs <hi>enhance the value</hi> of them in you. <hi>Great and grateful Effects,</hi> never fail to raiſe the price of <hi>Cauſes</hi> and <hi>Means.</hi> I mean with any but <hi>Idiots</hi> or <hi>Luna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks;</hi> Creatures of <hi>undiſpoſed</hi> minds or <hi>diſtracted</hi> ones.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="3" type="effect">
                        <p>
                           <label>E. 3.</label> 
                           <hi>This Conſideration ſtrengthens our Choice.</hi> Our choice of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, for <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Saviour.</hi> The ſight of our <hi>Tempted, Perſecuted, Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted</hi> Brethren here on Earth, is but too often a <hi>ſcandal</hi> unto us Makes our Hearts to ſtagger. Tempts us to <hi>go back, and follow Chriſt no more.</hi> But the Spiritual ſight of our <hi>Crown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> and <hi>Triumphant</hi> Brethren in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, hath on us a <hi>contrary operation.</hi> It ſtrengthens our <hi>Reſolution;</hi> and
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:39192:52"/>ſteels our <hi>Courage</hi> to truſt and obey him, who gave ſuch a Life and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unto them. It makes us, anew to reſign our ſelves unto him. Yea and bitterly lament, that we choſe him not more early and more fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vently.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="4" type="effect">
                        <p>
                           <label>E. 4.</label> 
                           <hi>This Conſideration quickens our Deſires.</hi> Our <hi>Deſires,</hi> and our <hi>Hopes.</hi> Our <hi>deſires</hi> to be, with Chriſt and his triumphant Friends above. And our <hi>hopes,</hi> that as laden with ſins as now we are, divine Grace may unburthen us at laſt, and lodge us with them. The thoughts of their wonderful Advancement will work, upon any Heart not <hi>ſtone dead.</hi> When carnal men think of any of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quals, that are riſen above them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>high Places,</hi> what is the effect? Why they are ſtraitway inſpired, with an <hi>unwonted Ambition</hi> for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. Yea and affected with a <hi>new Perſwaſion</hi> alſo, that 'tis as poſſible for themſelves to break through the difficulties which are in the way to
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:39192:52"/>
                           <hi>Preferment.</hi> Why ſhould not the <hi>Ambition</hi> and <hi>Expectation</hi> of Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al men, be excited by the ſame Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium? Surely, as <hi>Deſire and Hope are the ſprings of Action;</hi> glorious Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes of <hi>mean Agents</hi> be Springs of Deſire and Hope in their Spectators.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="5" type="effect">
                        <p>
                           <label>E. 5.</label> This Conſideration <hi>provokes our Diligence.</hi> The Victory of <hi>Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiades,</hi> took ſleep from the eyes of <hi>Themiſtocles.</hi> The thoughts of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers honour, ſpurred him on unto his more ſucceſsful Labour. And will not the matchleſs conqueſts of our glorified Friends, <hi>take our hands out of our boſoms?</hi> They will unqueſtion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, if they be conſidered ſolemnly. They will urge unto that holy <hi>Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence,</hi> without which the heavenly Kingdom cannot be taken.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="6" type="effect">
                        <p>
                           <label>E. 6.</label> 
                           <hi>This Conſideration ſweetens our Life of Religion. Joy,</hi> is our ſtrength. <hi>Heavineſs</hi> in the heart, <hi>weakens,</hi> if not <hi>binds</hi> our hands and feet. Indeed many <hi>Objects of God's Love,</hi> and <hi>true Saints,</hi> are of ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:39192:53"/>ſpirits. But the <hi>chiefeſt Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his glory,</hi> are, for the moſt part, Souls of <hi>much alacrity.</hi> To be ſure, whatever doth <hi>ſweeten,</hi> doth alſo <hi>heighten</hi> our Duty. For, Delight <hi>exonerates</hi> Body and Mind, <hi>takes off dulling Indiſpoſitions</hi> from them. Gives <hi>wings</hi> to both, and <hi>intends</hi> their actions. It doth marvelouſly, but as certainly encreaſe our <hi>Force</hi> to act, and our <hi>Accuracy</hi> in acting. <hi>Cogendi vis ineſt,</hi> ſaith <hi>Pliny;</hi> it makes the very <hi>Lame</hi> to walk, yea <hi>leap.</hi> For this reaſon it ſeems, that <hi>Muſick</hi> hath ever been uſed in <hi>Wars;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it doth delight; and, by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting, <hi>ſtrengthen the Nerves</hi> of fleſh and ſpirit. But what can delight a Soul that is any thing <hi>heavenly,</hi> like contemplation of the <hi>celeſtial Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty?</hi> For <hi>Contemplation</hi> doth, in a ſort, <hi>unite</hi> the Soul unto its Object. And, eminently, <hi>this Contemplation</hi> mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters <hi>Hope;</hi> which is the greateſt Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent of <hi>Joy,</hi> next to <hi>Fruition.</hi> When you are <hi>muſing</hi> of <hi>Heaven's Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants,</hi>
                           <pb n="93" facs="tcp:39192:53"/>your Soul has a <hi>place</hi> with them; and <hi>makes one among them.</hi> And you are in an <hi>exerciſe</hi> that makes you an <hi>Evidence</hi> of an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Manſion with them. <hi>Nero, Xerxes,</hi> and others, have propound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed rewards to the <hi>inventors of new Pleaſures.</hi> But he that ſhall diligent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make uſe of this, ſhall never pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound any. He ſhall ſay, I have <hi>Enough;</hi> yea, I have <hi>All.</hi>
                        </p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="7" type="effect">
                        <p>
                           <label>E. 7.</label> This Conſideration <hi>abates the Fear of Death. Morally</hi> it doth ſo; as it is of thoſe works, unto which <hi>ſafety from fear of evil</hi> is promiſed. The <hi>Promiſe</hi> hereof is as plainly made to <hi>good</hi> works, as the <hi>Threat</hi> of ſhame and fear is uttered againſt <hi>ſinful</hi> ones. And, thro' the grace of our Redeemer, hereof we are cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain: tho' <hi>holy</hi> thoughts and works deſerve not Conſolation, as <hi>ſinful</hi> ones deſerve fearfulneſs and horror; yet <hi>Grace</hi> gives as juſt an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of Comfort from the one, as <hi>Juſtice</hi> gives of Trouble from the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:39192:54"/>other. Beſides, even <hi>naturally</hi> this Conſideration abates the fear afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid. For they be the <hi>errours of Fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> by which Death is made <hi>exceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively</hi> formidable. Without a <hi>falſe repreſentation,</hi> it could not ſcare a <hi>true Chriſtian.</hi> But contemplation of our glorified Friends, doth <hi>confute</hi> the falſe ſuggeſtions of our Fancies. It repreſents Death in its true no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and ſo, by rectifying our <hi>Minds,</hi> fortifieth our <hi>Hearts, e. gr. Death,</hi> we cannot endure in our thoughts, becauſe we imagine it to be <hi>this threefold penance;</hi> to wit, <hi>the putting off a Body, without which we cannot live; the leaving of a World, that is the beſt we ever ſaw; and a going into a ſtrange Countrey and State of which our knowledge is very imperfect.</hi> Now <hi>due Conſideration</hi> of the heavenly Society and of our Friends in that glory, what doth it? If any thing, this it doth. It repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents <hi>Death</hi> as quite another thing, unto every good man. It demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:39192:54"/>it to be only <hi>the putting off of a Houſe of Clay, to enter and live in one made without hands; and therein joyfully to wait till the ſame is new built and added unto it. To be the leaving of a World, that next to Hell it ſelf, is the very worſt part of the Creation. And to be but a going home, not abroad; unto their Father and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, not to ſtrangers, and they know not whom. To a Countrey ſtrange but unto Senſe, not unto Faith. One, of which our knowledge muſt needs be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, becauſe the glory thereof is ſo very great, and our minds ſo weak.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe its <hi>eternal Poſſeſſions,</hi> exceed the capacity of our <hi>preſent Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandings.</hi> So that all who enter it, muſt do as great mens Heirs; who when they come to <hi>Age,</hi> go take in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their <hi>hands,</hi> more than in their <hi>minority</hi> they could conceive in their <hi>minds.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Thus is Death repreſented as a change, but for the better. One that doth not <hi>Hazard,</hi> but <hi>Accompliſh</hi> our
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:39192:55"/>greateſt Hopes. And ſo it becomes more the object of our <hi>Hope,</hi> and leſs the object of our <hi>Fear.</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>The uſes I make, I muſt croud into a narrow room. And preſent in a few Inferences and Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Learn ye hence.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="1" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 1.</label> 
                        <hi>The Neceſſity of Faith and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi> I name both, tho' the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle's word is, [whoſe FAITH fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low.] For he plainly means Faith in its <hi>Principle,</hi> and in its <hi>Effects</hi> and <hi>Exerciſes.</hi> Be theſe, either of them things indifferent? Or but ſmall, as Cummin and Aniſe? Indeed ſo they ſeem to be conceited, even in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and very <hi>London.</hi> But where be your eyes? See you not God's Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, and his multiplied motives un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to both? Is it conſiſtent with his <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs,</hi> thus, above all things, to call for things <hi>Needleſs?</hi> Do not dream So. If Satan could keep all men from theſe Jewels, he would ſhut up Heavens Gates; this is true if the Goſpel be ſo. The day is haſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:39192:55"/>which will convince you all; Fruit, without a Root, cannot be <hi>had.</hi> A Root, if without Fruit, cannot be <hi>valued.</hi> Without the Root and Fruit of Faith, no ſoul can be <hi>ſaved.</hi> Hell will ſhortly awaken you that ſleep and reſt long in <hi>Forms</hi> of Godlineſs. In empty <hi>names,</hi> in ſcenical <hi>ſhows,</hi> in dead <hi>opinions,</hi> in <hi>alamode</hi> cuſtomary <hi>Religion.</hi> O that Goſpel <hi>light,</hi> may prevent your Conviction by Hell <hi>Fire!</hi> Chriſt is able <hi>to ſave to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt.</hi> But <hi>Faith and Holineſs</hi> are his uttermoſt. And without them, He hath not <hi>will</hi> or <hi>power</hi> to ſave one Creature.</p>
                     <p>The <hi>Leper</hi> under the Law, typifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a <hi>Sinner.</hi> And he was to go with his <hi>Head uncovered,</hi> that he might be known of all men, and avoided. Theſe hints uncover the head of our <hi>Epidemical Sin.</hi> Fly you far from it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 2.</label> 
                        <hi>The Poſſibility of Faith and Holineſs.</hi> They are as <hi>Poſſible,</hi> as <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</hi> Hereof, every Soul got to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:39192:56"/>Heaven, is a clear Demonſtration. As we, ſo they all of them, had their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts of carnal Paſſions. From <hi>Nature, Temper, Education, ſecular Intereſt,</hi> they had them. But thro' the aids of the Holy Ghoſt, they <hi>took</hi> and <hi>held</hi> Holy Faith and Life. Some had a <hi>clearer</hi> and <hi>cleaner</hi> Victory than o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, but all were <hi>Victors.</hi> And <hi>their</hi> Victories, do prove <hi>ours</hi> to be poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble. They prove that the Enemies of Faith and Holineſs are not Uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querable; as <hi>Diogenes</hi> his walking, proved that motion was not a thing impracticable. Take heed, Brethren, take heed; and abuſe not the <hi>true do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> of your want of Power. Nor ever believe your danger of <hi>hell,</hi> to be ſo much from ought, as from your <hi>Will.</hi> Let D. <hi>Owen</hi>'s words be written on the Walls of your Houſes. They are upon Heb. 12.15. <q rend="margDblQuotes">
                           <hi>There is no man who under the profeſſion of the Goſpel comes ſhort of obtaining God's grace and favour, but it is by reaſon of himſelf and his own ſin. His negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:39192:56"/>ſloth, miſſing of opportunites, love of ſin.</hi>
                        </q> 
                        <hi>We have,</hi> as Merciful a <hi>God</hi> to deal with, as they that are got to Heaven had. We have the ſame <hi>Saviour</hi> and <hi>Sanctifier</hi> offerr'd, that they had. We have the ſame <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Sacraments</hi> miniſtred, as they had. Why ſhould we conceit our Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on impoſſible? Have a care Sirs, that you do not <hi>make it ſo!</hi> That, indeed, you <hi>may</hi> do. And are <hi>very like</hi> to do, if you heighten your corruptions by <hi>Cuſtom,</hi> enflame them by as <hi>wilful Temptation.</hi> And <hi>make</hi> them, more irreſiſtable than you <hi>find</hi> them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 3.</label> 
                        <hi>The Felicity of Faith and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs.</hi> How well do theſe end? We are called in the text to contemplate their End. And that, for the <hi>Glory</hi> thereof and for its <hi>Attractiveneſs</hi> of us. God cannot be <hi>God,</hi> if he ceaſe to be the <hi>rich rewarder</hi> of Faith and Holineſs. For he has ſworn by his Godhead; and <hi>pawned his Name of God upon it,</hi> that he will be the God of Believers and Obeyers of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel.
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:39192:57"/>The <hi>eternal</hi> Crown muſt fall off from his own Head, if an <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal</hi> one be not ſet on theirs. As ſin and Miſery, ſo Holineſs and Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs are inſeparable.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 4.</label> 
                        <hi>The untowardlineſs of men cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to Faith and Holineſs.</hi> Wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful! who has bewitched them? For, as our text ſpeaks not obſcure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they are hard to be <hi>enamored</hi> with the greateſt <hi>Beauty. Motives,</hi> and <hi>ſtrong</hi> ones they need, unto their moſt <hi>certain</hi> and <hi>greateſt</hi> good. The life of Faith and Holineſs, is the <hi>higheſt</hi> that can be in this low world. The <hi>beſt Heaven</hi> to be had <hi>on earth.</hi> And yet do we want a much better to allure us unto it. So dark is the Light that is in us. So, ſo have we loſt the firſt <hi>Light, Purity,</hi> &amp; <hi>Vigilance</hi> of our Minds, and the <hi>Rectitude</hi> of our Wills. Things deſpicable, inſinuate themſelves in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us very eaſily. Their <hi>faint color</hi> of profit or pleaſure, invades us with <hi>marvellous power.</hi> Power that
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:39192:57"/>raviſhes preſently the <hi>eſteem</hi> of our Minds, and <hi>Choice</hi> of our Wills. The lying vanities that do ſtill <hi>deceive</hi> us, can even <hi>compel</hi> us; and <hi>carry us whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> (we think at leaſt) <hi>we would not go.</hi> But, objects moſt <hi>amiable;</hi> in themſelves moſt <hi>excellent,</hi> and unto us moſt <hi>important;</hi> ſuch as deſerve the throne of our hearts; alas, how darkly do our <hi>Minds,</hi> repreſent theſe? how coldly do our <hi>Wills</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them? Till Omnipotence <hi>draws</hi> us, we never <hi>run,</hi> or <hi>go,</hi> or ſo much as <hi>look</hi> after them. A moſt humbling conſideration! We do need <hi>bit</hi> and <hi>bridle</hi> to keep us out of Satans crooked way, and <hi>ſpurs</hi> and <hi>goads</hi> to make us go in God's ſtrait paths.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 5.</label> 
                        <hi>The kindneſs of God to unto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward men.</hi> This, if any thing <hi>ſhines</hi> in my text and doctrine. For in what appeareth God's kindneſs, if not in his <hi>methods</hi> of calling us to Faith and Holineſs? Which are ſo admirably ſuited unto our weakneſs.
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:39192:58"/>So apt to <hi>reduce</hi> and <hi>engage</hi> the moſt extravagant Souls. So fitly qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as hath been before ſhewed, to make <hi>pliant</hi> the moſt obſtinate in evil, and to <hi>nail faſt</hi> the moſt irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute in good. Motives, even ſuch, the divine grace preſents. So it ſelf doth the dread <hi>Soveraign</hi> of the whole Creation, court every <hi>worm.</hi> Vouchſafing, not only to <hi>Will</hi> and <hi>Command,</hi> but to <hi>encourage</hi> and <hi>entice</hi> us unto Faith and Obedience. So making, that, if we will ſwim on in ſin unto Damnation; it ſhall be <hi>againſt the ſtream of grace</hi> in its <hi>utmoſt Condeſcention.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 6.</label> 
                        <hi>The Benefit of godly Miniſters and Friends.</hi> This, doth hence ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear great. Becauſe, not only <hi>Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> but <hi>Dead,</hi> they are unto us, great means of grace. As we may profit much by <hi>hearing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eſt aliquid quod à magno viro vel ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cente proficias. Sen. Ep.</hi> 94.</note> and <hi>ſeeing</hi> them, while they be here; we may do the ſame by <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring</hi> them when they
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:39192:58"/>be gone. It is our own fault, if it does not do us good to <hi>think</hi> of them. It is true, we may reap ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage from the thoughts of them, who to us were <hi>unknown.</hi> And of whom, and of whoſe Faith and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs we have only <hi>read</hi> or <hi>heard.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>They have well deſerved from <hi>the Church,</hi> whoſe <hi>Pens</hi> have preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of pious Perſons for us. Abroad, <hi>Melchior Adam, Theod. Beza,</hi> and others. At home, our immortal Martyrologiſt, <hi>Jo. Fox,</hi> Mr. <hi>S. Clark,</hi> Dr. <hi>Bates,</hi> Dr. <hi>Fuller,</hi> Dr. <hi>Lloyd,,</hi> &amp;c. That <hi>dunghil Spirits</hi> ſhould contemn their <hi>ſacred Pearl,</hi> is of no wonder at all. But that <hi>reputed Merchants for Heaven,</hi> ſhould grudg them their <hi>Money</hi> and their <hi>Time,</hi> is ſadly ſtrange. <hi>A Collection of the Characters of many moſt exemplarily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious,</hi> is now preparing in this City. Surely men of real Religion will pray for its <hi>good ſpeed;</hi> as conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it a very apt medium for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending unto us <hi>the City that hath
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:39192:59"/>better foundations,</hi> and for animating us to <hi>Live,</hi> to <hi>Suffer,</hi> and to <hi>Die</hi> for it.</p>
                     <p>But it may not be denied, and it ought to be conſidered; Great is the power of <hi>Acquaintance</hi> and <hi>Converſe!</hi> Our thoughts have by far the <hi>eaſieſt</hi> and <hi>ſweeteſt</hi> acceſs unto them in Heaven, that we had <hi>moſt friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> with upon Earth.</p>
                     <p>In a word, <hi>Pearls,</hi> are but the ſhining <hi>Froth</hi> of the Sea; as <hi>Silver</hi> and <hi>Gold</hi> be but the <hi>White and Yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Duſt</hi> of the Earth. An <hi>Holy Friend,</hi> is an incomparably <hi>richer</hi> thing, and more <hi>ſerviceable.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="inference">
                     <p>
                        <label>I. 7.</label> 
                        <hi>The Praiſe of Conſideration.</hi> Which thus here meets us. It is by the ſacred Writer made the <hi>ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pital means</hi> of our excitation, unto the things which are our <hi>Life.</hi> Yea, of our excitation unto them by the moſt <hi>powerful motive.</hi> It is by him made as neceſſary, to our being benefited by God's Word, as <hi>Eating</hi> is neceſſary, to our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:39192:59"/>
                        <hi>nouriſhed</hi> by <hi>Bread.</hi> For his phraſe is to be underſtood, as if the Text had plainly ſaid; <q rend="margDblQuotes">The bleſſed End of your holy Prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors, take you into juſt &amp; deep conſideration; without which, it can no more <hi>affect you,</hi> than a <hi>Beauty</hi> and <hi>Treaſure</hi> can affect one that neither <hi>ſees</hi> nor <hi>hears</hi> of them. Nor any more <hi>draw forth your hearts</hi> to imitate their Faith, than <hi>Chains</hi> or <hi>Cords</hi> can draw forth of their places, things that they take no hold of.</q>—Indeed the uſefulneſs of <hi>Conſideration,</hi> is <hi>ſelf-evident;</hi> nor need words, for <hi>information's ſake,</hi> be multiplied. All men grant, that every <hi>good Act</hi> is a product of <hi>ſtated Judgment,</hi> not of a <hi>ſudden raſh</hi> Thought: and <hi>ſtated Judgment it ſelf</hi> is the iſſue of <hi>ſerious Perpenſion,</hi> the ultimate and moſt perfect Act of our Reaſon, or Think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing faculty. But, <hi>interpretative Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction</hi> is the <hi>rife Plague</hi> among us. Moſt men, <hi>ſleep in their groſs
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:39192:60"/>Inconſideracy,</hi> and are <hi>ſtrangers unto true Contemplation.</hi> And it is to be feared, ſome are vain and wild enough, to expect benign <hi>infuſions</hi> of the <hi>Holy Spirit,</hi> without the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired <hi>conſiderations</hi> of <hi>their own.</hi> Miſerable deluſion! For, He is a ſpirit of <hi>Wiſdom;</hi> that is, of wiſe Thoughts. Not <hi>a ſpirit ſent to make Fools;</hi> that is, creatures ſpending <hi>no</hi> Thoughts, or but <hi>few</hi> and <hi>ſlight</hi> ones, on the things of their Peace. His work is, to make wiſe, and to ſet at rights our Thoughts. To wit, as to the <hi>Objects, Qualities, Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, Orders,</hi> and <hi>Ends</hi> of them. In a word; He that <hi>eats</hi> not neceſſary Bread, is dead naturally, and he that <hi>conſiders</hi> not neceſſary Truth, is dead ſpiritually. <hi>Spare</hi> Meals make <hi>ſlender</hi> Bodies; and <hi>ſlight</hi> Meditations make <hi>lean</hi> Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Wouldeſt thou be much edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by thy glorified Friends Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples? then contemplate them much. Expecting not holy <hi>Impul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi>
                        <pb n="107" facs="tcp:39192:60"/>from a few <hi>roving Thoughts!</hi> Without much muſing, no holy fire burns. Precious <hi>Metals</hi> and <hi>Jewels</hi> are produced, where the Beams of the Sun are <hi>moſt ſtrongly</hi> reflected; and there it is that hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Affections</hi> are kindled, where <hi>apt Thoughts</hi> are moſt <hi>vigorouſly</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed.</p>
                     <p>Now, in his Name whoſe we <hi>Are;</hi> whom we <hi>Serve;</hi> and to whoſe Tribunal we <hi>Haſten;</hi> I ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hort as follows.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Let not worthy Mr. HURST, or any other Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, be without a <hi>Religious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument</hi> in your Hearts. <hi>Former Ages</hi> have exceeded bounds in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of deceaſed Friends. <hi>Papiſts</hi> abide ſtill in their Exceſſes. But, abhorring them, run you not into a contrary peccant Extream! <hi>Idolize</hi> your Friends in glory, you may not; <hi>honourably</hi> and <hi>affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately remember</hi> them, you muſt.</p>
               <p>Your duty is, to follow their
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:39192:61"/>
                  <hi>Faith,</hi> not their <hi>Fancies.</hi> And their <hi>holy Walks;</hi> not their <hi>wry Steps.</hi> They were but <hi>Men;</hi> our fellow-ſervants, and not our <hi>Maſters.</hi> Nor are they to be followed by us, far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than they followed their and our <hi>one Maſter.</hi> It ſhall be Praiſe now, and Glory in the day of your accounts, if you conſider their <hi>Chief End,</hi> and aim at the ſame. The <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>Mediator,</hi> and the <hi>Comforter</hi> that they choſe; and do chuſe the ſame. The <hi>Goſpel-Covenant</hi> that they ſtudied, lived upon, and by; and do ſtudy, and live upon the Promiſes, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Demands of the ſame. If you exerciſe daily the <hi>Faith</hi> you have ſeen in them, the <hi>Hope</hi> and the <hi>Love;</hi> the <hi>Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance,</hi> the <hi>Diligence,</hi> and the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience;</hi> the <hi>Humility,</hi> the <hi>Juſtice,</hi> and the <hi>Charity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The holy things which ye have both <hi>Learned</hi> and <hi>Received,</hi> and <hi>heard</hi> and <hi>ſeen</hi> in them, <hi>do ye;
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:39192:61"/>and the God of Peace ſhall be with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ou.</hi> After ſevere ſtudy of the way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Heaven, they neither wilfully <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>andred out of it,</hi> nor <hi>ſlothfully <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>alked in it.</hi> Take you their <hi>Way,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd their <hi>Pace;</hi> and hold both. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mitate you their <hi>Watchfulneſs</hi> over your <hi>Hearts</hi> and your <hi>Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>es,</hi> and their <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> of both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſaulting <hi>Temptations,</hi> and conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing <hi>Corruptions.</hi> They did, as the Army of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which, paſſing thorough a Wood abounding with <hi>Honey,</hi> would not taſte it, becauſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he King had forbad them. <hi>The people feared the King's Oath,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 14.26. They choſe rather <hi>Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions,</hi> than <hi>ſinful Pleaſures;</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>roaches for Chriſt,</hi> rather than the <hi>Treaſures of Aegypt.</hi> Love you the <hi>World,</hi> and the <hi>things of it,</hi> as little is they loved them. They under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the diſproportion between a ſpiritual Nature, and carnal Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſualities: and looked not on Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral things, as the goods of im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortal
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:39192:62"/>Souls. Pray, as hard <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> they prayed for the Peace of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem!</hi> Loving the Church; as knowing they were to be judged by their Affections unto the ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering Churches. Not confining God's Church unto their own <hi>Party;</hi> nor making their unneceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary <hi>Opinions Articles</hi> of Faith, and their unneceſſary <hi>Modes</hi> of Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>Terms</hi> of Communion. Let it not be ſaid, that <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, was theirs, more than yours. As they, ſo do you reſolve, to ſerve God with your <hi>Houſholds</hi> commanded ſo to do. Educating your <hi>Children</hi> piouſly and prudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Loving your <hi>Servants</hi> Souls, with care to ſave them; and uſing <hi>them</hi> in all references, as you would be uſed <hi>your ſelves,</hi> if you were in their conditions.</p>
               <p>Contemplate <hi>ſeriouſly</hi> and <hi>fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently,</hi> (as before directed,) the bleſſed ſtate of which they are now
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:39192:62"/>poſſeſſed. Spend not all the thoughts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ou have to ſpare, upon their <hi>Life.</hi> Of the two, beſtow them moſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erally upon the Eſtate they entred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto at their <hi>Death.</hi> And do not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ndure your <hi>Living Friends,</hi> to take from you the time in which you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hould remember your Dead ones. <hi>Take it for no leſs a duty to Commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Dead, than to viſit the Liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</hi> To Commemorate the <hi>Place</hi> where they be, the <hi>Company</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they dwell, the <hi>work</hi> wherein they are employed. And <hi>ſtay</hi> ye ſometimes in theſe thoughts, when you form them; as you uſe to ſtay in viſits of your Neighbours, when you make them. Start not <hi>out</hi> of theſe uſeful thoughts, aſſoon as you are got <hi>into</hi> them. As tho' you dream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that little benefit and comfort could be expected from them. Reſt not till you have overcome the firſt <hi>ſhyneſs</hi> of your minds. Their <hi>ſtrange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> unto theſe thoughts. Yea, till <hi>ſenſible benefit</hi> hath made them im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patient,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:39192:63"/>of keeping <hi>long</hi> from them, A little <hi>ſerious exerciſe</hi> will make them ſo.</p>
               <p>For, to ſay the truth, which ſome tell me they feel; and which I have felt as my great motive, both to Preach and Publiſh this haſty diſcourſe. Theſe thoughts are moſt exceeding helps, to <hi>faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate</hi> and to <hi>ſweeten</hi> our thoughts of God, with whom is dazling and overwhelming Majeſty. Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> calls them our <hi>ſtepping-ſtones;</hi> and <hi>ſtairs of aſcent</hi> to look at God. And a greater than he, doth (me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks) direct us to eye the <hi>glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied Saints,</hi> as a ſweet mean to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote looking unto <hi>Jeſus Chriſt, Heb.</hi> 12.1, 2. Unto <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who is our <hi>only</hi> and perfectly <hi>ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient Mediator.</hi> His glory, dare you not for your lives to give unto his moſt glorified Members. But, neither dare you to neglect ſuch remembrance of thoſe his <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi> as ſo makes for the honour
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:39192:63"/>of Him the <hi>Head.</hi> As is both an <hi>Evidence</hi> of your Principle of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs toward Him; and a <hi>Means</hi> of its Practice and Progreſs.</p>
               <p>The promotion of which <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, Practice,</hi> and <hi>Progreſs,</hi> is the dutiful <hi>Deſign</hi> of every Sermon. And may it be the plentiful <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> of this Occaſional one unto you! <hi>Amen</hi> and <hi>Amen!</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="afterword">
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>THE foregoing <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> hath preſſed the <hi>Remembrance of departed Saints Glory,</hi> without any thing ſaid of <hi>departed Sinners Miſery.</hi> Becauſe I had purpoſed to treat thereof <hi>diſtinctly</hi> and as <hi>fully,</hi> from another Text. But, opportunity being here given me, I take it to ſay thus much.</p>
            <p>Of the Means of Grace, all are
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:39192:64"/>
               <hi>Excellent,</hi> but none <hi>Superfluous.</hi> They do, all, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ualifie</hi> and <hi>Engage</hi> us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the uſe of each other. No one excuſeth from the uſe of another. It hath been ſhewn to be <hi>highly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficial,</hi> to ſtir up our ſelves, by the conſideration of deceaſed Saints <hi>Bleſſedneſs,</hi> unto an imitation of their <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Holineſs.</hi> And it is as <hi>certainly profitable</hi> to urge our ſelves, by the conſideration of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Sinners <hi>Ruine,</hi> unto an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horrence of their <hi>Unbelief</hi> and <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Reaſons</hi> are both obvious and numerous. So are convincing <hi>Obſervations</hi> and <hi>Experiences.</hi> He was an eminently pious Antient that thus beſpake his Auditory; Sirs, <q rend="margSglQuotes">Let us be oft going down to Hell in our contemplations while we live that our Souls may not go down into it when we die.</q> And I have heard our greateſt Divines praiſe another; who having found that exerciſe very helpful againſt his Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:39192:64"/>did not ſtick to exclaim, <q rend="margDblQuotes">O Lord, my Soul doth bleſs thee for Hell!</q>
            </p>
            <p>It is true, <hi>the Hope of Heaven is the ſweeteſt Perſuaſive;</hi> but, it is as true, that <hi>the Fear of Hell is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly the ſtrongeſt Motive,</hi> to our Duty. <hi>Unregenerate hearts,</hi> do feel little but this latter. And the <hi>moſt ſanctified men alive</hi> will tell you; that they are fain, under moſt of their Conflicts, <hi>to call in their Fear to the help of their Hope.</hi> And that their Life is <hi>a Flying from the Wrath to come,</hi> as well as <hi>a Laying up Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To clear this, let it be obſerved. The <hi>Objects of Hope</hi> are leſs con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivable by our minds, than <hi>thoſe of Fear</hi> be. Although <hi>Storms</hi> and <hi>Darkneſs</hi> be without any difficulty pictured; <hi>Calms</hi> and <hi>Sun-ſhines</hi> can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be drawn without exquiſite Art, and extreme Induſtry. <hi>Hell's Torments</hi> be a thouſand times more eaſily underſtood, than <hi>Heaven's
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:39192:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>Joys</hi> and <hi>Glorys</hi> be. The Imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a natural Man, will fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully repreſent <hi>the burning Fire, and the gnawing Worm.</hi> But <hi>the fulneſs of Joy in God's preſence, and the ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting Pleaſures at his right hand,</hi> theſe are <hi>fooliſhneſs</hi> unto him, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>can</hi> he know them. No Eye but a <hi>Spiritual</hi> one; and that <hi>ſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hard in deep Contemplation,</hi> can diſcern much of them. Alas! who is it that can ſay, he needs not all the helps preſcribed in Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Saints Everlaſting Reſt?</hi> (part 4th. page 219. unto page 242.) I mean his Helps to conceive affectionately of the Heavenly Glories.</p>
            <p>Theſe things premiſed, I exhort unto the Duty eaſily inferred. Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>frequent</hi> and <hi>moſt ſerious</hi> Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of <hi>impenitent Sinners end,</hi> as well as of <hi>penitent Believers. Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turaliſts</hi> ſay, that the attractive ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the <hi>Loadſtone</hi> is leſs when it is ſingle; and draweth much more ſtrongly, when it is encom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſed
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:39192:65"/>and armed with <hi>Iron.</hi> You ſhall find, I am very ſure, that the <hi>Hope of Heaven</hi> will much better <hi>draw</hi> you, when the <hi>Fear of Hell</hi> doth conjunctly <hi>drive</hi> you.</p>
            <p>Briefly, Having here no more room, I adviſe to a juſt meditation of theſe three particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is an Hell, as ſure as there is an Earth.</hi> There be <hi>damned men Burning,</hi> as ſure as there be <hi>ſinning men Breathing.</hi> Yea, and as many of them, as have ever died in <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitence,</hi> and <hi>Unbelief,</hi> and <hi>Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. Chriſtians</hi> and <hi>Jews</hi> alſo believe this. So do <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Pagans,</hi> for the ſubſtance of it. The <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oran</hi> mentions a houſe of Perdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. <hi>Plato</hi> ſpeaks almoſt the words of Holy Scripture; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Hell is the Center of Miſery.</hi> A Collection of <hi>all</hi> evils in their <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igheſt</hi> degrees. Paſſing all our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent underſtanding; foraſmuch as
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:39192:66"/>not comprehending <hi>what an incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God can do,</hi> 'tis impoſſible to comprehend <hi>what a Damned man doth ſuffer.</hi> A man that eternally <hi>Dies</hi> and <hi>Lives</hi> together; having <hi>a Death without End,</hi> and <hi>a Life with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Eaſe.</hi> And <hi>Tortures</hi> too, without, and beyond, all compariſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Hell or Center of Miſery hath ſix Memorables; e. gr.</hi> 1. <hi>Its Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Names.</hi> A <hi>Priſon,</hi> bottomleſs <hi>Pit,</hi> ſecond <hi>Death,</hi> never dying <hi>Worm,</hi> unquenchable <hi>Fire.</hi> 2. <hi>Its Eſſentials. Deprivation</hi> of all good; of Drops of <hi>Water,</hi> as well as Cups of <hi>Wine:</hi> and <hi>Accumulation</hi> of all evils; for the Veſſels of Wrath are filled with it. 3. <hi>Its Efficients.</hi> The <hi>Place, Company,</hi> and enraged <hi>Conſcience</hi> are grievous ones; but God's own <hi>immediate hand</hi> is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivably the ſoreſt, and ſtrikes the hardeſt blows. (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee Dr. <hi>Tho Good win</hi> hereof.) 4. <hi>Its Concomitants.</hi> Theſe are an <hi>Enlargement</hi> of mind and a <hi>Fixedneſs</hi> of it upon torment<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:39192:66"/>Objects. God lets in upon the Damned a great <hi>Light,</hi> to exaſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>te their <hi>Fire.</hi> There, <hi>Ignorance</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould do them a kindneſs; ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ould one minutes <hi>Forgetfulneſs.</hi> But it cannot be. Here they <hi>would <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> know God, there they <hi>muſt.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere they <hi>would not Think</hi> of him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere <hi>they cannot ceaſe</hi> one moment <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om thoughts of him. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re feel nothing but confounding <hi>Shame,</hi> piercing <hi>Sorrow,</hi> racking <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ury,</hi> and <hi>Deſpair</hi> that is beyond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Epithets. 5. <hi>Its Duration.</hi> And this is FOR EVER. An <hi>Eternity</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>expreſſable as its <hi>Extremity.</hi> 6. <hi>Its <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nds and Reaſons.</hi> Which are, the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>estraining of Sin</hi> in the World; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the ſhewing forth God's <hi>Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſs, Righteouſneſs,</hi> and <hi>Power,</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Sinners finally incorrigible.</p>
            <p>Indeed, if we ſaw all the <hi>Bleſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ining</hi> in Heaven, and all the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>amned burning</hi> in Hell, as daily and plainly as we ſee any thing with our Eyes; it could not <hi>make
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:39192:67"/>us Holy</hi> without the gracious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the Holy Spirit. But, be it conſidered; that bleſſed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of his is not to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, without the uſe of his preſcribed <hi>Contemplations</hi> and <hi>Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices.</hi> It is by <hi>Heaven</hi> and <hi>Hell,</hi> both of them, in our <hi>Thoughts,</hi> that he pleaſeth to rectifie our <hi>Affections</hi> and <hi>Works.</hi> Let us there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, neither <hi>Pray</hi> for his Grace without <hi>Meditations,</hi> of both, nor <hi>Meditate</hi> of both without <hi>Prayers</hi> for his Grace.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <p>
               <hi>NB.</hi> The Marginal Note page 59<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> was by the Printers miſtake inſerted. The ſubſtance of it being found page 60 and 61 in its proper place.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:39192:67"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:39192:68"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
